<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of the Quakers relating to oaths stated wherein they are discovered, to oppose propheticall, to pervert evangelicall, to falsifie ecclesiasticall, and to contradict their own doctrine / by J.S.</title>
            <author>J. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60994</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S48</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2531</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13173433</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13173433</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98333</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60994)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98333)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 777:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of the Quakers relating to oaths stated wherein they are discovered, to oppose propheticall, to pervert evangelicall, to falsifie ecclesiasticall, and to contradict their own doctrine / by J.S.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98333:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98333:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF THE QUAKERS RELATING TO OATHS STATED.</p>
            <p>Wherein they are Diſcovered, To oppoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall, To pervert Evangelicall, To falſifie Eccleſiaſticall, and To contradict their own Doctrine.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J.S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feb.</hi> 17. 1673.</p>
            <p>Imprimatur, <hi>Auto, Saunders, Ex Aedibus Lambothauis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Brome,</hi> at the Signe of Gun at the Weſt End of S. <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:98333:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98333:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THe Envious man finding the whole Fabrick of our Church too heavy a burthen to bear away at once, divided the work of her ruine to the heads and ſhoulders of many Inſtruments; committing to one Sect the ſtudy to pull up her hedge, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other the atempt to overthrow her doctrine; to another the care to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermin her worſhip: And becauſe their reſpective tasks ſtill proved too difficult for any one of theſe Parties to compaſſe alone, he ſubdivided theſe Provinces to ſubordinate Vice-gerents; allotting to one the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing of her Ceremonies, to another the vilifying of the ſubſtance of her common and ſtated Devotions, to another the oppoſing of her extraordinary and moſt auguſt acts of Sacred Worſhip; amongſt which the Invocation of Gods Name in Solemn and Religious Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fell to the <hi>Quakers</hi> Lot; who being a Generation of men that ſtick in the bark of the letter, admitting neither coherence of Texts nor analogy of faith; and ſtumbling upon two Texts that abſtracted from both theſe, ſeem to favour their Opinion, have with raiſed out-crys attempted to explode that Catholick Cuſtome of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, of giving God the honour of appeal to his Omniſciency; for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpirage of ſuch controverſies, as by his Ordinance cannot be determined without an Oath: For the Redemption of theſe ſacred ſpoils out of their Sacrilegious hands, I have undertaken this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, and entred upon this Race, wherein the Prizes I run for, are, <hi>Firſt,</hi> The maintenance of this Ancient Truth (diametrical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:98333:3"/>oppoſite to their new Errour, ſo farre as by their canting I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> discern their minds,) <hi>viz,</hi> That Chriſtians of the higheſt rank as greateſt proficiency, may lawfully (in ſone caſes) confirm the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Oath. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Vindication of the Evangelical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings frim falſe gloſſes. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Demonſtration of their a faithfulneſſe, on their Quotations of Eccleſiaſtical Teſtimonies in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of their Cauſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98333:3"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTION I.</hi> Chriſtians of the higheſt rank and greateſt Proficiency, may lawfully in ſome caſes confirm the Truth with an Oath.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. SAint <hi>Paul</hi> both knew the minde of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23 <hi>And ſerved God in the ſpirit, in the Gospel of his Son, Rom.</hi> 1.9. yet he was ſo far from pleading that of the <hi>Eſſenns</hi> mentioned by <hi>Joſephus, Bell. Jud. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7. who profeſs'd, that <hi>[quicquid dixerint validius eſſe omni juramento &amp; ſupervacuum eſſe ipſis jurare]</hi> their word was ſtronger then the oath of other men, and therefore it was ſuperfluous for them to ſwear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Or that of the <hi>Scythians,</hi> who told <hi>Alexander</hi> (as <hi>Quintus Curtius</hi> reports) that their love of veracity was ſo eminent, as their affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a thing was in ſtead of an Oath. Or the cuſtome of the Heroick Age wherein (as <hi>Homer</hi> relates) the ſhaking of their Sceptre or ſhaking by the hand, did more oblige men to ſpeak the truth, and perform promiſes, then the moſt ſacred Oaths could oblige ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding degenerate Ages. So far (I ſay) was S. <hi>Paul</hi> from plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch examples or his own exemption from his performance of this office of charity, to common humane infirmity, which in many caſes requires the interpoſiton of an oath in order to the procuring an indubitable perſwaſion of the truth: as he frequently confirms what he aſſerts in ſuch like forms of ſacred oaths as theſe, <hi>[God is my witneſſe,]</hi> Rom. 1.9. <hi>[I ſay the truth in Chriſt, I lie not, my conſcience alſo bearing me witneſſe in the holy Ghoſt]</hi> Rom 9.1. [<hi>I call God for a record upon my ſoul, that,</hi> &amp;c] 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23. <hi>[The God and father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt knows that I ly not]</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.37. <hi>[As God is true our word towards you, was not yea and nay.]</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18. <hi>[Before God I ly not] Gal.</hi> 1.20 <hi>[God is my record] Phil.</hi> 1.8. <hi>[Ye are witneſſes and God alſo]</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. upon which St. <hi>Auſtin, Jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit autem ipſe Apoſtolus in Epiſtolis ſuis, &amp; ſic oſtendit quomodo accipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98333:4"/>quod dictum eſt. [Non Jurate omnino.]</hi> (Auguſtine <hi>de mend. cap.</hi> 15.) for the Apoſtle himſelf did ſwear in his Epiſtles, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by demonſtrate, how that is to be underſtood where it is ſaid, <hi>ſwear not at all.</hi> That theſe forms of ſpeech are ſacred oaths, is manifeſt from <hi>Geneſis</hi> 31.50.53. where <hi>Laban</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> are ſaid to ſwear in theſe forms of words <hi>[So God is witneſſe betwixt men and thee,]</hi> and [<hi>the God of</hi> Abram, <hi>the God of Nahor, the God of their fathers judge betwixt us</hi>] and [<hi>Jacob ſware by the fear of his father</hi> Iſaack, that is, by God whom his father worſhipt. And (to ſpare the labour of making more quotations) from the definition of an oath: which in Philo's phraſe <hi>(de legibus particularibus)</hi> and in the common notion of mankinde, is nothing elſe but a calling of God to witneſſe to the truth of what we ſay. From which, if eminency of Holineſſe would excuſe any man, it would have excuſed S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who before the writing of thoſe Epiſtles, had given greater teſtimony of his ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, veracity, and love to truth, then any man living can (either in truth, or with Chriſtian modeſty) lay claim to. Who can have the face to ſay? That he hath delivered the truth with greater <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the ſpirit and of power,</hi> in <hi>words which the Holy Ghoſt teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4.13.) That he hath, <hi>by manifeſtation of the truth, commended himſelf to every mans conſcience in the ſight of God</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.) more, then this choſen veſſel did? which of them, that tell us, we may take their word and ſpare their oath, dares vie with him in the perills, pains, hardſhips, labours, loſſes, which he ſuſtain'd for the truths ſake? If then S. <hi>Paul</hi> (notwithſtanding Chriſts prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that he could pleade more for mens taking his bare <hi>yea and nay,</hi> then any man now living can pleade) did yet frequently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm his ſayings with an oath; what more then <hi>Eſſaean,</hi> then <hi>Scythian,</hi> then <hi>Luciferian</hi> pride, poſſeſſeth thoſe monſters of men, who have the impudence to pleade their own eminency in grace, as that which exempts them, from calling God for a record againſt their ſoul, when the conſiderableneſs of the thing requires it; From exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting to the divine Majeſty that part of incommunicable honour due to his ſacred and dreadfull name. Away with that ſmoakie pride out of Gods houſe, let it not be ſo much as named amongſt Saints, whoſe character is humility.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ang.</hi> 2. Without the interpoſition of an oath 'tis impoſſible in many caſes that Juſtice can be adminiſtred according to the rule of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98333:4"/>the Goſpell. To inſtance in one for all. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.10, 11. <hi>[If a man deliver unto his neighbour an oxe, or aſs, or ſheep to keep, and it die, or be hurt, or driven away, no man ſeeing it: then ſhall an oath of the Lord be between them both, that he hath not put his hand to his neighbours goods, and the owner of it ſhall accept thereof, and he ſhall not make it good.]</hi> It is the righteous Gods will, that Juſtice be adminiſtred, in this, and the like caſes, now under the Goſpell, as well as formerly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law: but in ſuch like caſes, it cannot be determined accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Evangelical rule, who ſhall bear the loſſe, without the interpoſition of an oath. For if the mans bare word be taken for the proof of his innocency, the controverſy will be decided by one onely witneſſe: directly againſt Chriſts precept: <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.16. <hi>That in the mouth of two or three witneſſes every word may be eſtabliſht.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the guiltleſſe party, in ſuch caſes as this (where no man but himſelf is privy to his innocency) muſt in vindication thereof, take in God to witneſs with him: that ſo the matter may be decided by two witneſſes at leaſt, to wit, by him that makes oath, and by God whom he calls to witneſſe with him. Breifly we muſt either make Chriſt by this prohibition <hi>[ſwear not]</hi> to patronize ſuch injuſtice under the Goſpell, as God would not patronize under the law; or proceed to the determination of controverſies contrary to Chriſts rule: or elſe put an end to ſuch like ſtrife, by the interpoſure of an oath. And therefore ſwearing in ſuch caſes is ſo far from being a ſin, as it is a neceſſary duty, not to be neglected without manifeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice: to the preventing whereof, and the doing of right betwixt man and man, nothing is more contributary then Evangelicall grace: ſo far is ſanctity from exempting its poſſeſſors from the diſcharge of thoſe offices of charity, which they owe to themſelves and their neighbour in ſuch caſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. That which the ſpirit of Chriſt in the old Teſtament. Prophets (1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.11.) did commend, as that which ſhould be the practiſe of the choiſe ſervants of God in the Chriſtian Church called from amongſt the Gentiles, after his rejection of the Jewes, may lawfully be done by the holieſt Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>But the ſpirit of Chriſt in the old Teſtament-Prophets did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend ſwearing by the God of truth, as that which was to be the practiſe of Gods elect ſervants in the Chriſtian Church, after his rejection of the Jewes and chooſing the Gentiles.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98333:5"/>
               <p>Therefore the holieſt Chriſtian may lawfully ſwear by the God of truth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>major</hi> is undeniable, the Aſſumption I prove, from <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 65.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>[And ye ſhall leave your naine for a curſe to my choſen]</hi> that is, The peoople that I ſhall chooſe from amongſt the gentiles ſhall uſe, your name (the name of a Jew) in execrations, when they have a minde to denounce a curſe, they ſhall do it in this or the like form, <hi>[the Lord make thee like a Jew whom he hath caſt off and made a vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond upon erath]</hi> parllel to that, <hi>Jeremy</hi> 29.22. <hi>of them ſhall be taken up a curſe</hi> (that is, the form of a curſe) <hi>by all the captivity of</hi> Judah; <hi>ſaying, the Lord make the like</hi> Ahab <hi>and</hi> Zedekiah (two falſe prophets) <hi>whom the king of</hi> Babylon <hi>roſted in the fire. [For the Lord God ſhall ſlay thee and call his ſervants by another name,]</hi> that is, God will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the <hi>Judaick</hi> Church &amp; Common-wealth, ſo that his people ſhall no longer be diſcriminated from the reſt of the world by the name <hi>[Jew]</hi> but by another new name that which was given at <hi>Antioch,</hi> where the diſciples were firſt called Chriſtian, by which name ever ſince the people of the God of <hi>Abram,</hi> have been called and diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renc't from all other people upon the face of the earth. <hi>[That he who bleſſeth himſelf in the earth, ſhall bleſſe himſelf in the God of truth: and he that ſweareth in the earth ſhall ſwear by the God of truth.]</hi> The ſum of this whole Paragraph is breifly this. You Jewes boaſt of your priviledged, of my electing you out of all Nations to be my pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar people; and you pleaſe your ſelves with theſe conceits, that if I caſt you off, I ſhall have none to worſhip me in the whole world, I ſhall break my promiſe made to <hi>Abraham.</hi> But know ye that <hi>Abraham</hi> hath another ſeed then carnal Jews; and when I caſt you off I will take the ſpirituall ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> (his children by faith), to be my people; who ſhall be known from others by the name, [Chriſtian] by theſe I will be ſecured, not (as I am now by you) in a corner of the world, <hi>Judaea,</hi> but in the earth, <hi>for the uttermoſt parts of the earth ſhall be my poſſeſſion,</hi> and whoſoever through the wide world, under the Chriſtian name, ſhall call upon the name of the true God, <hi>ſhall beleſſe themſelves in his name, and ſwear by him as the God of truth,</hi> as the God, who by chooſing gentile-beleevers to be his people, keeps faith with <hi>Abraham.</hi> See <hi>Calvin,</hi> S. <hi>Jerom,</hi> in <hi>locum. Oecolampadii hypomnemata,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. That which the ſpirit of Chriſt, that was in the prophets
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98333:5"/>foretold ſhould be done in the time of the Goſpel by the Lords people, as an evidence of their converſion unto the Lord, may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be done by Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>But the ſpirit of Chriſt which was in the prophets foretold that in the time of the Goſpel, the Lords people ſhould ſwear by his name, as an evidence of their converſion unto the Lord.</p>
               <p>Therefore a Chriſtian may lawfully ſwear by the Lords Name.</p>
               <p>The <hi>major</hi> is beyond all poſſibility of doubt, if it be conſidered how it is limited, for I do not ſay, that whatſoever the prophets fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told ſhould come to paſſe, may lawfully be done (for I know they foretold the treaſon of <hi>Judas,</hi> the Jewes rejecting of Chriſt, &amp;<hi>c.</hi>) but, that whatſoever they foretold ſhould be done as a ſigne of grace, as an evidence of their converſion that do it, may be done without ſin: For ſin cannot be an evidence of grace; works of darkneſſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not demonſtrate him that does them to be a childe of light. The truth of the <hi>minor</hi> is clear, from Jſaiah 45.23. <hi>I have ſworn by my ſelf, the word is gone out of my mouth in righteouſnceſſe, and ſhall not return</hi> (ſhall never be repeal'd) <hi>that unto me every knee ſhall how, every tongue ſhall ſwear.</hi> From which Text that I may manifeſt the indubitable truth of each branch of my aſſmption, Let it e obſerved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That this propheſie is to receive its accompliſhment in goſpel times. For God ſpeaks here <hi>to the ends of the earth,</hi> bids them <hi>look to him and he ſaved,</hi> promiſeth ſalvation to the Gentiles, calleth the diſperſed of the nations to come near, and ſweareth that <hi>every knee ſhall bow unto him.</hi> Now the ends of the earth the nations diſperſed did not look to God, were not brought nigh till Goſpel-times, till then not the gentile world, but onely the Jewiſh people did <hi>bow the knee and ſwear to the God of Iſrael,</hi> to the Lord <hi>Jehovah.</hi> Before the coming of Chriſt and the gentiles embracing the Goſpel, they were <hi>without God, aliens and ſtrangers to the common-wealth of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the Covenants of promiſe, afar off,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That ſwearing to the Lord is here propheſied of, as that divine ſervice and homage, by the performing whereof gentile-converts were to declare their owning of, and converſion to the true God. St. <hi>Paul</hi> quotes this very Text to prove that all inen (Gentiles its well as Jewes) owe ſervice to Chirſt, <hi>Rom</hi> 14, 9, 10. <hi>He is Lord of all</hi> (that is all nations are to do him homage) for it is written, <hi>As I live (ſaith the Lord) every knee ſhall bow to me, and every tongue ſhall confeſs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98333:6"/>to God.</hi> It were blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt to ſay, that the Apoſtle perverts the prophets words: but he knowing the minde of the Lord in this text, renders that word in the prophet, <hi>[every tongue ſhall ſwear,]</hi> (which denotes an eminent act of ſaving confeſſion) by a word which comprehends the whole ſervice of God: thereby im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying that ſwearing by the Lord is one part of divine worſhip, and ſo eminent a part of confeſſion to God, as it virtually contains all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acts of ſuch confeſſion; and that we confeſſe our beleif in, and ſubjection to the true God, as well by ſwearing by his name, as by any other act of divine worſhip we perform to him. Breifly, the plain ſenſe of the prophet, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> expounds this text, is this, That as the Gentiles, till Chriſt (that light that lightens the gentiles) ſerved dunb idols, confeſſing them to be Gods, by bowing the knee, by ſwearing to them: ſo after Chriſts calling the gentiles to the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the true God, man ſhould turn from idols, &amp; acknowledge the living God to be, what his names and attributes import, infinitely knowing, juſt, powerful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by transferring unto him thoſe divine honours, of bowing the knee and ſwearing, which before their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, they confer'd upon falſe Gods.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That God himſelf ſwears by himſelf (then which infinite wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom cannot deviſe a more obliging oath) that the Gentile-Church as well as the Jewiſh ſynagogue ſhould by ſwearing to the Lord <hi>maks confeſſion with the mouth unto ſalvation,</hi> that by two immutable things he might more abundantly ſhew unto the heirs of the promiſe the immutabilitie of this his Councill and predetermination, that Chriſtians ſhould homage him with this kinde of divine ſervice: and give them as full aſſurance as 'tis poſſible for God to give of the acceptableneſs of this part of ſacred worſhip, And if this be not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to put an end to all controverſie touching this queſtion, [whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Chriſtian may lawfully take an oath,] I ſhall deſpair of ever prevailing with ſuch obſtinate and reprobate-minded men, by the plaineſt demonſtratious I can lay before them: for how can I hope to convince him with the ſtrongeſt reaſoning, who dare reaſon againſt Gods oath: Howbeit, That the matter to which God here ſwears (to wit, that under the Goſpell mon ſhall, in token of their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the living God, ſwear to him) may be more plain; I ſhall give a further proof there of out of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 19.18. &amp;c. <hi>In that day ſhall five Cityes in the land of Egypt ſpeak the language of Canaan, and ſwear
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98333:6"/>to the Lord of hoſts: There ſhall be an altar to the Lord in the mideſt of the land of Egipt, and a pillar to the Lord at the border thereof. And it ſhall be for a ſigne and for a</hi> Witneſs <hi>unto the Lord of hoſts in the land of Egipt. For they ſhall cry unto the Lord, and he ſhall ſend thens a Saviour. And the Lord ſhall be</hi> known <hi>to Egipt, and the Egiptians ſhall</hi> know <hi>the Lord in that day, and ſhall do ſacrifice and oblation, yea, they ſhall Vow a</hi> Vow <hi>unto the Lord and perform it, and he ſhall be entreated of them, and ſhall heal them.</hi> Upon which text I note.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That this propheſie concerns Goſpell-times, <hi>Onias</hi> indeed that mock-high-prieſt, alledged this propheſie to <hi>Ptolomy Philometer,</hi> and applied the accompliſhment of it to that mock-temple which he built at <hi>Heliopolis,</hi> in imitation of that at <hi>Jeruſalem, Joſeph. Antiq. l.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 6. and that diſcreet and ſober Jewiſh prieſt <hi>Joſephus</hi> himſelf in his Jewiſh wars (<hi>l.</hi> 7 <hi>c.</hi> 30.) ſeems to approve of that interpretation. But how wide ſuch Expoſitors were of the mark of truth, and how unapplicable this Propheſie is to any time, but that when <hi>Egypt</hi> was called by the preaching of the Goſpell to the acknowledgement of the true God, hath abundantly been demonſtrated by <hi>Euſebins</hi> in his <hi>Demonſtratio Evangelica,</hi> and the reſt of the antient Chriſtian Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſts, upon theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Cnias</hi> erected an altar in <hi>Egypt</hi> out of a factious oppoſition to the true high prieſt <hi>Simeon</hi> and the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> Jewes of his communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and occaſioned a ſchiſm from the <hi>Jadean</hi> Church, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> confeſſeth: <hi>Bell. Jud. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 30. But the effect of erecting the altar mentioned in this propheſie was the uniting the Egyptians and Jewes into one Church, verſe. 23. <hi>In that day</hi> (when this altar ſhall be erected to the Lord in the mideſt of <hi>Egypt</hi>) <hi>there ſhall be an high way out of Egipt to Aſſyria, and the Aſſyrians ſhall come into Egypt and the Egiptians into Aſſyria, and the Egiptians ſhall ſerve</hi> (the Lord) <hi>with the Aſſyrians. In that day ſhall Iſrael be the third with Egypt and Aſſyria, even a bleſſing in the midſt of the land: whom the Lord of hoſts ſhall bleſs, ſaying, bleſſed be Egipt my people, and Aſſyria the work of my hand, and Iſrael mine inheritance. Nunc Chriſto regnante torus mundus uno altari contentus eſt: (Oecolampad.)</hi> now under Chriſts kingdom the whole world is content with one altar.</p>
               <p n="2">2. After God had choſen out <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for the place where he would be worſhipt, the Jewes were prohibited by the Moſaicall law to ſacrifice any where but there; And therefore all the ſacrifices that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98333:7"/>were offered upon the altar, that <hi>Onias</hi> erected in <hi>Egipt;</hi> were an abomination to the Lord. But God promiſeth in this text, to have reſpect unto the oblations offered upon this altar, whether by Jew or Gentile; and therefore the acceptable ſacrifice and oblations here mentioned, can be no other then that pure oblation, which after the coming of Chriſt ſhould every where be offered, when Gods name ſhould be great amongſt the Gentiles, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.11. Nor the altar here ſpecified any other then that which S. <hi>Paul</hi> mentions, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.10. <hi>We have an altar whereof they have no right to eat, which ſerve the taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle;</hi> that is, Chriſts Table-throne of grace, whereon we offer to God his Creatures of bread and wine, and in the Sacramental uſe of them, celebrate the commemoration of Chriſts one oblation of himſelf once made for all, and our ſelves unto God, as a living ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, together with our contributions of charity, a ſacrifice where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God is well-pleaſed. <hi>Reſpondeant Judaei, lege praeceptum eſt ut altare non ſiat niſi in loco, quem elegerit Dcus, &amp; hoſtiae tantum a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotibus Levitici generis immolentur. Ecce</hi> Eſaias <hi>aperte decet qued Aegiptii colent Deum &amp; hoſtias &amp; mumera offerant. Si Aegiptii Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotium habeant; impletur &amp; in illis Pauli teſtimonium dicentis: tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sacerdotio, neceſſe eſt ut leg is tranſlatio ſiat.</hi> Hieronymus <hi>in locum.</hi> Let the Jew, if he can, anſwer this, ſaith S. <hi>Jerome,</hi> In the Law there was a precept, that no altar ſhould be ſet up but in the place that God ſhould chooſe; and that the beaſts ſhould be ſacrificed only by the Prieſts of <hi>Levies</hi> ſtock; But lo <hi>Eſaias</hi> ſaith plainly, that the <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſhall offer ſacrifices and oblations; If the <hi>Egyptians</hi> have a Prieſthood, that Teſtimony of S. <hi>Paul</hi> is fullfilled in them, ſaying, If the Prieſthood be changed, there muſt of neceſſity be a change alſo of the Law.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Not the <hi>Egyptians</hi> but the Jews ſacrificed on that altar which <hi>Onias</hi> erected: but upon the altar to be erected, according to the tenure of this propheſie in <hi>Egipt,</hi> the <hi>Egiptians</hi> were to do ſacrifice and make oblation unto the Lord.</p>
               <p n="4">4. During the continuance of the Moſaical law and the ſtanding of <hi>Onias</hi> his temple and altar in <hi>Egipt,</hi> and before the erecting of the Chriſtian altar and the ſtandard of Chriſt in <hi>Egipt,</hi> the <hi>Egiptians</hi> cried for ſalvation unto their Idols not unto the Lord, made vows to them, ſware by them: they ſpake the language of the heathen not of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan:</hi> neither had they a Saviour ſent unto them, till God ſent Chriſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98333:7"/>to bleſſe them. Nor did <hi>Iſrael, Egipt, Aſſyria,</hi> and other gentiles ſerve God together in the communion of one Catholick Church. Nor did God bleſſe the Gentiles (as he promiſeth here he would bleſſe the <hi>Egiptians</hi> and <hi>Aſſyrians</hi>) by the name of his people, till Chriſt took down the partition-wall, made of twain (Jew and Gentile) one bodie, and called them a people that were not formerly the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God. It is manifeſt out of S. <hi>Jerom,</hi> (upon this text) who converſt with the Paleſtine Jewes, that their Expoſitors applyed this text to the dayes of the Meſſias: but when our Apologiſts upon that conceſſion proved the bleſſed Jeſus to be the Chriſt; ſome of them applied it to the end of the world: at what time they conceive their Meſſias will come, upon the very ſame miſtaken ſcripture-texts, upon which our Millenaries ground their expectation of Chriſts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal reign.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I note from this propheſie: that ſwearing to the Lord is here commended as a ſigne, witneſſe, and argument of <hi>Egipts</hi> converſion to the Lord of hoſts: <hi>And it ſhall be for a ſigne and for a witneſſe to the Lord in the land of Egipt,</hi> that is, it ſhall be à witneſſe that the land of <hi>Egipt</hi> is become the Lords inheritance, that the Egiptians have dedicated themſelves to the Lord: that he is their God and they his people, <hi>[It ſhall be for a ſigne]</hi> this hath relation to the whole clauſe afore-going: not onely to the pillar erected, which is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ond immediatly before, as if the ſenſe were <hi>[this pillar ſhall be a ſigne]</hi> for the altar in the midſt of <hi>Egipt,</hi> the <hi>Egiptian</hi> Cityes, <hi>ſpeaking</hi> the language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and their ſwearing to the Lord, are as much ſignes as that: Nor doth the prophet ſpeak in the plural number <hi>[they ſhall be ſignes]</hi> as if he meant the two laſt particulars joyn'd by a conjunction copulative, the altar and the pillar, but in the ſingular <hi>[It ſhall be a ſigne]</hi> that is, the whole ſeries of thoſe divine diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations; when the Egiptian cityes ſhall ſpeak the holy language, when they ſhall ſwear to the Lord, erect an altar and pillar to the Lord, this ſhall be a ſigne of <hi>Egipts</hi> ſubmitting to Chriſts ſcepter. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil alud vult, quam mutatum cultum idolorum &amp; tranſlatum in honorem Dei.</hi> Oecolam. <hi>in locum.</hi> the meaning of all this is, that divine honour and worſhip which they had given to their idols, they ſhould alter the propertie thereof, and transfer it to the true God. Is any thing more obvious then that <hi>Egypts</hi> ſwearing, erecting altars and pillars to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, was a ſigne of her owning thoſe Idol Gods? or that <hi>Egipts</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98333:8"/>ſpeaking the language of Gods people, ſetting up an altar and pillar to the Lord, her making vowes and paying them, her offering ſacrifice and oblations to the Lord, were trophyes of Chriſts victory over <hi>Egipt,</hi> and ſignes of <hi>Egypts</hi> ſubmiſſion to Chriſt: with what ſhow of reaſon then can we except ſwearing to the Lord out of the catologue of thoſe ſignes, ſeeing that is ſpoken with the ſame breath, belongs to the ſame thing, and therefore muſt be put in the ſame caſe, and be interpreted, (<hi>Monumentum, &amp; profeſſio publica quam Egiptii, ſtatuent ad teſtandam fidem &amp; communionem ſuam cum Deo &amp; Eccleſia ejus,</hi> Junius <hi>in locum.</hi> as well as any of the reſt: A monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and publick profeſſion which the <hi>Egiptians</hi> were to erect to reſtify their faith and their communion with God and his Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Swearing to the Lord is in this Text made a branch of ſpeaking the language of <hi>Canaan. They ſhall ſpeak the language of Canaan,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſwearing by the name of the Lord,</hi> as the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Tranſlation of the <hi>Septuagint</hi> renders it, which Chriſt and the Apoſtles perpetually uſed in all their quotations of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, as that which had been current through the world for above 200. years before Chriſts Incarnation, without contradiction of the Jewes, and not ſo obnoxious to adulteration afterwards, as the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Copies were, who were in the cuſtody of the Jewes alone, and in a language which none underſtood but themſelves; and therefore as apt to be corrupted, as the Jewes (out of an <hi>odium</hi> to Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) were apt to corrupt them: as it is manifeſt they have done in moſt of thoſe Texts which concern the <hi>Meſſias;</hi> though this by good providence hath eſcap't their lime-twigg-fingers: for the Hebrew now extant retains the participle, <hi>jurantes;</hi> So that to ſwear by the Lord of hoſts is to ſpeak the language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> that pure lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage which God promiſed to reſtore to all Nations at the coming of Chriſt; <hi>That pure and undefiled Religion which was at firſt reveal'd to man in Paradiſe;</hi> for before Chriſt all Nations but the Jews, the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſware by other Gods, and to ſwear by the <hi>Lord of hoſts</hi> was the proper <hi>idiom</hi> of <hi>Jury,</hi> where that God was well known. I know <hi>Jerom</hi> hath a conceit that <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> after his conqueſt of <hi>Egipt,</hi> ſent a colonie of <hi>ſyrians</hi> &amp; <hi>Arabians</hi> into certain <hi>Egiptian</hi> cities, who introdue't the uſe of their tongue into thoſe Cityes; But he learnt this of the Jewiſh tradition-mongers (of whom he was too great an admirer, and through his credulitie received oftentimes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98333:8"/>falſe aimes) who put this Expoſition upon this clauſe, on purpoſe to divert it from bearing witneſſe to the truth of the Goſpell. And he muſt be a very great ſtranger to the propriety of prophetick language, that knows not, that the language of <hi>Canaan</hi> imports in their dialect the ſpeaking after the mode and form of Gods people, and that therefore <hi>Egipts</hi> foregoing her native gentile-tongue, and uſing the ſpeech of that people, over whom God had a peculiar Soveraignty, in ſwearing to him after their form, was a ſigne of Gods conqueſt of the <hi>Egiptians,</hi> of his tranſlating them from his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Satan into the Kingdom of his dear Son: ſo farr is ſwearing by <hi>the Lord of hoſts,</hi> or in the name of the true God, in caſes of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, from being a ſin, as it is an evedence of the Chriſtian worlds converſion to, and recognition of that God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. The holieſt Chriſtian may lawfully, and laudably do that, which the ſpirit of Chriſt that ſpake by the prophets, hath made the doings of in Goſpell-times, the condition of Gods accepting men for his people.</p>
               <p>But the ſpirit of Chriſt in the Prophets hath made mens learning to ſwear by his name, ſuch a condition, as upon the fulfilling thereof, he will number men amongſt his diſciples, account them his people that do, and root out and utterly deſtroy them that do not learn to ſwear by his name.</p>
               <p>Therefore the holieſt Chriſtian may lawfully ſwear by Gods name.</p>
               <p>The <hi>major</hi> is plain, for it is impoſſible that God ſhould tempt men to ſin by making the committing thereof the condition of the grand and comprehenſiye promiſe, ſuch as this is of being his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which includes all the beneſits and priviledges of that relation. This were to allure us to ſin by ſtronger motives then Satan can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly lay before us.</p>
               <p>The <hi>minor</hi> I prove from <hi>Jeremy</hi> 12.16. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs that if they will diligemly learn the ways of my people, to ſwear by my name</hi> (in this or the like form) <hi>the Lond liveth; as they taught my people to ſwear by</hi> Baal, <hi>then ſhall they be built in the midſt of my people; but if they will not obey, I will utterly pluck up and deſtroy that nation, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is beyond all poſſibilty of rational doubt, that this Propheſie relates to the time of the Goſpel, for it is directed to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> of whom Gods people had learnt to ſwear by <hi>Baal,</hi> called by God,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98333:9"/>
                  <hi>his evil neighbours, verſ.</hi> 14. that is, Nations bordering upon <hi>Judea,</hi> his own inheritance, his own land, whom he blames for touching the inheritance which he had cauſed his people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to inherit, that is, for turning the Jews out, and taking to their own poſſeſſion the Holy Land, as did the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> and their confederates in the Jewiſh Wars, the <hi>Samaritans, Phoenicians, Ammonites, Edomites,</hi> &amp;c. whom he threatens to pluck out of their own land, as they had dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Jews out of theirs, and to pluck out the houſe of <hi>Judah</hi> from amongſt them: this God perform'd at their reſtauration from the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilonian</hi> captivity: To theſe Gentile-borderers (I ſay) God directs this threat, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord againſt all my evil neighbours that have touched, &amp;c.</hi> and this promiſe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſſe, after that I have plucked them out, I will return, and have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion upon them, and bring every man to his heritage, and his own land.</hi> After the mention of which reſtauration of thoſe Gentile-borderers, doth immediately follow this promiſe, <hi>and if they will learn the ways of my people, to ſwear by my name,</hi> &amp;c. This promiſe then concerns that time when God would return to, and have compaſſion on the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, when he would call her beloved that was not beloved, and them a people that was not a people, and is made to them! that had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the worſhip of the true God to their Idols, in whom they had perſwaded them to put confidence, by whom they had taught them to ſwear, in ſuch forms, <hi>as Baal liveth, by the life of Baal,</hi> &amp;c. and manifeſtly imports this ſenſe. If as you Gentiles have taught my people (the Jews) to ſwear by your Gods, you will learn of them (when the law ſhall go out of <hi>Sion</hi> into all the world, by the miniſtry of the Apoſtles) to ſwear by my name, then you ſhall be built up amongſt my people. Yea, the matter of this promiſe being the ingrafting of the gentiles into the Church, the luying of them as living-ſtones in Gods ſpiritual temple, the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets in the midſt of Gods people: it could not poſſibly take effect while the partition-wall ſtood, nor have its accompliſhment till Chriſt by the blood of his Croſſe had removed the enmity, and making peace, had reconciled both Jew and Gentile unto God, in one body. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A dilligent learning to ſwear by Gods name, is here made the condition of Gods promiſe of grafting the gentiles into the ſtock of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98333:9"/>
                  <hi>Abraham,</hi> of his accounting them his ſpirituall ſeed, of his building them up amongſt his people, of his giving them a name and a place in his houſe: as being that which is the way of Gods people, nay the ways of Gods people, the Old Teſtament-way and the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament way, of their proteſting what God they ſerve, in contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction to the ways of all other people; each of which ſwear by the name of that falſe God, whom they reſpectively ſerved; and in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction from all other ways of confeſſing the true God: men may confeſs God in prayer, in thankſ-giving, in attendance upon the Word and Sacraments, and yet not glorifie him ſufficiently, in order to Gods accepting of them as true worſhippers, in order to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting them living-ſtones, fit to be laid in the walls of his houſe, the Church; except to thoſe forementioned and all other wayes of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing their homage, they adde this, of <hi>ſwearing by his name,</hi> except withal they dilligently learn to acknowledge his omniſciency, omaipo: encie, juſtice, and divine vengeance, by appealing to thoſe dreadful attributes, by ſwearing by his fearful name, when they are lawfully thereunto called, where this moſt ſolemn invocation of the divine majeſty is denied him; he eſteems all other acts of invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation not ſerious enough to oblige him that tenders them to a ſincere confeſſion: Men may poſſibly diſſemble in their bare word-profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of God and his attributes, and therefore he puts Chriſtians here to the utmoſt trial of their ſincerity, by this moſt awful addreſs to him: He that ſwears by his Name, calls God for a witneſs againſt his ſoul, dares him to his face, challengeth the divine vengeance to do its worſt, in caſe he ſwear falſly; and therefore God eſteems this as the higheſt and moſt auguſt act of Divine worſhip that the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can poſſibly exhibite to him, and as that which eminently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains all others, and comprehends the whole condition of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, all the ways of Gods people confeſſing to him. Hence S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.12. interprets, <hi>qui jurant in eo,</hi> by <hi>qui ſit Chriſtianus,</hi> he that ſwears by him, that is, (ſaith he,) every profeſt Chriſtian: <hi>Nam juramentum ſumitur pro toto cultu ut in</hi> Eſai. 45.23. <hi>jurabit omnis lingua;</hi> for ſwearing by God implies the whole worſhip of God, as in <hi>Iſaiah; Every tongue ſhall ſwear to me;</hi> which is the reaſon why he ſingles out this leſſon, as that which whoſo learns diligently, ſhall have the beneſit of the book, be numbred: with Saints; be written amongſt the living in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> be built up as a lively ſtone in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98333:10"/>midſt of Gods people; or if you will have it in <hi>Davids</hi> phraſe, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 63.12. <hi>Every one that ſweareth by him, ſhall glory</hi> or (as the Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint is rendred in our Liturgy) <hi>ſhall be commended</hi> as precious ſtoner, oppoſed to refuſe ſtones: But I overdo my undertaking, in glving reaſons, why God makes the learning of this leſſon, the condition of this promiſe: It is ſufficient to juſtifie ſwearing by Gods Name, from the imputation of ſin, that it hath pleaſed him, to make the learning thus to ſwear, the condition of his accepting us as ſincere diſciples, of his ingrafting us into his Evangelical Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The not learning thoſe ways of Gods Old and New-Teſtament people, <hi>to ſwear by his Name,</hi> the non-acceptance of this graclous propoſal, the non-uttending to thoſe terms, the not-obſerving of this condition, the not-obeying God in obſerving the command here implied, of diligently attending to learn the way of confeſſing to God, renders men obnoxious to the dint of this fearful doom: <hi>I will utterly pluck up and deſtroy that nation, ſaith the Lord:</hi> whatever Nation or generation of men, (be they Familiſts, Anabaptiſts, Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts, Quakers) will not learn diligently to ſwear <hi>by the name of God,</hi> to ſwear <hi>the Lord liveth,</hi> and the like Chriſtian forms, they may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps bolſter one another up with vain hopes, of Gods accepting them, with groundleſs preſumptions, that they are the people of God; but God doth here reject them, and diſmounts all their proud confidences; thoſe <hi>Babol</hi>-builders architects of confuſion, may ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then one anothers hands in carrying up their caſtles in the air, in: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their <hi>Sodom</hi>-vines, but when their backſlidings from the common faith are multiplied to the full ſum, when their meaſure of apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is filled up, when God hath by theſe his ſcourges debated to his meaſure with his Church, for her humiliation and purgation, and has done his work, his whole work upon mount <hi>Sion,</hi> that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to make them inſtrumentall to; he will pluck up all ſuch plants, pull down all ſuch buildings, and utterly deſtroy all ſuch people. He <hi>who wilt not hold him guiltleſs that takes his name in vain,</hi> will not let them eſcape unpuniſht, who will not learn to ſwear by it, <hi>in judgement, righteouſneſſe, and truth.</hi> They ſhall periſh who run foul upon this <hi>Scylla,</hi> as certainly, as they who fall into that <hi>Caribdis.</hi> A truly-ſanctified conſcience ſteers a middle courſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe extreams, and while it fears an oath, in vain and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane ſwearing, after the guiſe of heathens, fears alſo not to learn
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98333:10"/>this way of Gods people, to ſwear religiouſly by his name. To this courſe we are directed by the compaſſe not onely of thoſe texts that I have alledged, but of thoſe alſo which are urged by the Quakers, and out of which they ſqueeze objections againſt this propheticall doctrine, which the holy Men of God, <hi>who ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> have thus plainly delivered: which that I may make manifeſt, it will be requiſite that we take the meaſure of thoſe Evangelical Scriptures which are forced to ſpeak againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECTION II. The Texts which they commonly urge, are.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>S.</hi> Mat. <hi>5.34.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>But I ſay unto you, ſwear not at all, neither by heaven, for it is Gods throne, neither by Jeruſalem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But let your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication be yea, yea; nay, nay; for whatſoever is more then theſe, cometh of evill.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>S. James 5.12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Above all things, my brethren, ſwear not at all, neither by heaven, nor earth, nor any other oath, leſt ye fall into condemnation.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> 1. IF I would argue <hi>ad hominem</hi> or (in <hi>Solomons</hi> phraſe) <hi>anſwer a fool according to his folly:</hi> I need give no other ſolution of their paralogiſms grounded upon theſe texts then this: They deal with theſe texts, as the devil did with that which he quoted to Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.6. out of <hi>Pſa.</hi> 91.11. <hi>He ſhall give his angels charge over thee, &amp;c.</hi> For as he perverted that to a damnable ſenſe by leaving out that eſſentiall part of it, <hi>In all thy ways,</hi> So theſe men wreſt thoſe porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Seripture, by making a ſtop at <hi>ſwear not at all,</hi> and leaving out the words following, <hi>neither by heaven, &amp;c.</hi> which were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the ſame breath and are an eſſential part of the ſentence: which entirely ſtands thus: <hi>ſwear not at all, neither by heaven not earth,</hi> &amp;c. and prohibits ſwearing at all, by theſe or any other creatures. But what makes this againſt ſwearing by the Lord? here is nothing forbid, but what was forbid in the law, when ſwearing by the Lord was not only lawful, but expreſly commanded, as the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors confeſſe, and is manifeſt from <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. and 10.29. yet then ſwearing by them that were not God, was prohibited, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98333:11"/>charged upon the Jews as a ſin, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 5.7. <hi>how ſhall I pardon thee for this? thy children have forgotten me, and ſworn by them that are no Gods.</hi> Heaven, Earth, <hi>Jeruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> are not God, and therefore Chriſts ſorbidding us to ſwear by them or any other creature, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent as well now as it was formerly with the command of ſwearing by the Lord. And whereas they urge that of S. <hi>James, nor any other oath,</hi> as if that made any kinde of oath unlawful; there is nothing more obvious to him that piouſly ſearcheth the minde of God in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred writ, then this obſervation: That there are many propoſitions laid down in general terms, whoſe ſentence muſt be limited to the matter in hand, or elſe they manifeſily contradict the light of nature, and other ſacred Texts. As, when Chriſt ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 10.8. <hi>All that ever came before me were theives and robbers.</hi> If we expound that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without any limitation at all, we muſt neceſſarily thence infer; that <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> were thieves, for they came before Chriſt: But if we confine it to the ſubject on which Chriſt diſcourſeth, <hi>viz. I am the door, the way,</hi> &amp;c. then the ſenſe will be found as importing no more but this, that all who came before Chriſt, pretending that they were, <hi>the door, the way,</hi> that is, the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> the Chriſt, or that great ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were theives. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>all things are lawful for me,</hi> if, by <hi>all things</hi> we underſtand all things without exception, it will follow, that it was lawful for him to ſteal, lie, mnrder, blaſpheme, and what not; when he ſaith, <hi>I become all things to all men,</hi> if we expound his words without limitation, the conſequence will be, that he became a drunkard, an Epicure, an Atheht, an Apoſtate, to gain ſuch kind of men. But if we limit thoſe ſayings to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject upon which he treateth in thoſe places, the ſence will be ſuch as becoms the Apoſtle of the holy Jeſus, <hi>viz.</hi> all things that God hath not prohibited, ſuch as I am now ſpeaking of, are lawful for me, I am at liberty to do them, or leave them undone, as ſtands moſt with conveniencie, ſo far as either <hi>Jew, Grecian,</hi> or <hi>Barbarian,</hi> retain any true principles, I am theirs, and urge thoſe principles, as my own, upon them, in order to my drawing them to embrace the goſpell. So when S. <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>nor by any other oath,</hi> this univerſal muſt be limited to the preceding words, <hi>viz. ſwear not by heavener earth,</hi> and contains a prohibition to ſwear by any other oath of that ſort which he had named, but not any other ſort of oath as that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98333:11"/>from of oath is, which I urge the lawfullneſſe of, for it is apparent that S. <hi>James</hi> doth here epitomiſe the ſaying of Chriſt in S. <hi>Matt.</hi> and having mention'd ſwearing <hi>by heaven or earth,</hi> he comprehends the remainder of Chriſts inſtances, <hi>ſwearing by the temple, by Jeruſalem, or the hair of our head,</hi> in this abbreviation, <hi>or any other oath,</hi> as if he had ſaid, ſwear not at all, by heaven, earth, or any other of thoſe forms of ſwearing, by the creature, that Chriſt forbad the nſe of, in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on the mount, when he publiſht his royall law, or indeed by any form of that kinde. From the bare letter therefore of theſe texts, nothing can be inferred contradictory to my aſſertion, for they prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit ſwearing by any creature, and I maintain the lawfulneſs of ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Lord of all creatures: and to them that ſtick in the bark of the words themſelves, as the Quakers do, no other anſwer need be given to ſtop their mouths, but this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> 2. But that I may ſatisfie perſons of more ſober mindes, and ſpeak the whole and naked truth, <hi>ex animo,</hi> I give this as the full and adequate anſwer to all fanatick reaſonings from theſe Texts, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſolemn and reverential ſwearing, that Chriſt and S. <hi>James</hi> are ſo far from prohibiting the reverential uſe of Gods name in ſolemn oaths, as they eſtabliſh it, while they forbid all irreverentiall ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by ſo much as Gods creatures, forbid to ſwear at all, though it be but by the creature lightly, and in common diſcourſe, upon this reaſon, becauſe he that ſwears by heaven, ſwears by him whoſe throne it is; he that ſwears by earth, ſwears by him whoſe footſtool it is, becauſe, though Gods name be not expreſly menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in ſuch forms of oaths, yet it is implied, and therefore we are not to uſe ſuch forms in our common ſpeech, any more then the name of God himſelf, which in the opinion of all but profeſt Athieſts, is not to be ſworn by, but with reverence, and in extreme neceſſity. For the removal of ambiguity and ſtating the caſe, before I come to prove this aſſertion, let me premiſe theſe obſervations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Scriptures make a wide diſſerence betwixt ſwearing by the true and ſwearing by a falſe God, in point of lawfulneſſe: but none in point of the obligatorineſs of the oath; becauſe he that ſwears by a falſe God does conceive him to be the true, and under that notion appeals to his heart-ſearching knowledge, omnipotency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore the true God interprets it as an aſſront offered to him, when perjury is committed, in the uſe of the name of an idol: Excellent is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98333:12"/>that obſervation of the imitator of <hi>Solomon, Wiſdome</hi> 14.28. <hi>The</hi> worſhippers of idols do <hi>lightlie forſwear themſelves; for inſomuch as their truſt is in idols which have no life: though they ſwear falſlie, yet they look not to be hurt: Howbeit for both cauſes ſhall they be juſtly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; both becauſe they thought not well of God, giving heed to idols; and alſo unjuſtly ſwore in deceit, deſpiſing holineſs; For it is not the power of them by whom they ſwear, but it is the juſt vengeance of ſinners, that puniſheth alwayes the offence of the ungodly;</hi> underſtand him to ſpeak of the Athieſtical Idolater; for as to the ſuperſtitious Pagan, he thinks that Idol he ſwears by to be a god in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; <hi>prorſus perjurus es quin per illud quod ſanctum putas falſum juras:</hi> Auſt <hi>de verb apoſt. Ser.</hi> 28. thou art altogether perjured, becauſe thou ſweareſt falſly by that which thou thinkeſt is holy. Hence, as Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Grotius</hi> obſerves, the people of God would never ſwear by the Gods of the Gentiles, but if they, with whom they made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract by oath, could not be induced to ſwear otherwiſe, themſelves would ſwear (as they ought) by the true God, and take an oath from the gentile, ſuch as could be had: which yet they looked upon to be as good a ſecurity, in reſpect of its obliging the gentiles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as their ſwearing by the true God was, in reſpect of its ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging their conſcience: as we ſee in the covenant betwixt <hi>Laban</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> where <hi>Laban</hi> ſwore <hi>by the God of Chaldea,</hi> but <hi>Jacob By the fear of his father Iſaack,</hi> to put it beyond all doubt, that he ſwore not by that God whom <hi>Nahor, Terah,</hi> and even <hi>Abram</hi> himſelf wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt, before his call out of <hi>Chaldea;</hi> for <hi>Iſaack</hi> never fear'd or ſerv'd other God but him, who made heaven and earth; and yet he accounts <hi>Labans</hi> oath to oblige <hi>Laban</hi> to the performance of the covenant betwixt them, as well as his oath did oblige himſelf, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.53. Hence that ſaying of <hi>Sophocles</hi> in his <hi>Hippodamia: the minde is incited by ſwearing diligently to avoid two evils, to be blamed by men, and to offend the Gods:</hi> and that of <hi>Cicero,</hi> Offic. 3. <hi>quod affirmate qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi Deo teſte promiſſeris, idtenendum eſt: thou muſt keep that which thou poſitively promiſes before God as witneſſe.</hi> Hence perjury amongſt the heathens is reckoned amongſt thoſe crying ſins, which divine venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance never permits to eſcape unpuniſht, and which ſometimes God viſits upon the poſterity of guilty parents.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to the forms of ſwearing, whether Gods name be expreſly mentioned in them or only implied, by mentioning ſome of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98333:12"/>with reſpect to him: as when we call <hi>earth</hi> or <hi>heaven,</hi> &amp;c. to bear witneſs to what we ſay. I do not ſinde any diſſerence made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, either in point of lawfulneſſe or obligation, by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, or God himſelf, in any age, either that before the law, or that under the law, or this under the Goſpel. So far were the Old-Teſtament-Saints from thinking the uſe of ſuch like forms (wherein not God but the creature, with relation to God, was named) to be prohibited by, and a tranſgreſſion of that divine law. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God, and ſerve him, and ſhalt ſwear by his name;</hi> that is, onely, as our Saviour expounds that text. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.10. As the holyeſt of them never ſcrupled to uſe ſuch forms themſelves, or gave the leaſt hint of their diſguſting that practiſe in others. The good <hi>Shu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amite</hi> ſware <hi>by the life of Eliſha,</hi> 2 King. 4.30. <hi>As the Lord liveth, and as thy ſoul liveth: Eliſha by the life of Elijah,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Hannah by the life of Elie.</hi> 1 Sam. 1.26. <hi>As thy ſoul liveth my Lord I am the woman.</hi> Abner <hi>by the life</hi> Saul, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.55. <hi>As thy ſoul liveth, oh King, I cannot tell.</hi> Abigail <hi>by the life of</hi> David, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.22. <hi>As the Lord liveth, and as thy ſoul liveth:</hi> Uriah <hi>by the life of</hi> David, 2 <hi>Sa.</hi> 11.11 <hi>Perſalutem tuam &amp; per ſalutem animae tuae non faciem hanc rem; By tby health, and by thy ſouls health, I will not do this thing.</hi> It were endleſſe to give all the Inſtances that offer themſelves.</p>
               <p>And if the New-Teſtament-Church had not been of the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſior, <hi>viz.</hi> that ſuch kindes of Oaths are not compriſed in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition either of <hi>Moſes</hi> or Chriſt, S. <hi>Paul</hi> would not have let that form fall from his pen, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.31. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I proteſt by your rejoycing,</hi> or more properly, <hi>I ſwear. Ambiguitatem Graecus ſermo diſſolvit;</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> well obſerves, <hi>Serm.</hi> 28. <hi>in verb. Aboſt.</hi> The greek text removes all ambiguity, for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in that tongue is a note of ſwearing, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>per Jovem,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>per Deum:</hi> you converſe (ſaith he) daily with <hi>Grecians,</hi> and though you cannot ſpeak nor underſtand greek, yet this you underſtand, that a <hi>Grecian</hi> ſwears when you hear him ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and therefore let none of you doubt but that the Apoſtle ſwears, when you hear him ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I ſwear by your rejoycing:</hi> Nor would the Primitive Chriſtians, (who (under the Pagan perſecutions,) rejoyced to ſuffer the moſt exquiſite tormerts that witty malice could invent, rather then be perſwaded to ſwear by the heathen gods, or the <hi>Genii</hi> of the Emperours,) have ſworn (without the leaſt ſcruple of conſcience) by the health
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98333:13"/>of the Emperour; (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apology for them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Gentiles, cap.</hi> 32.) aſſureth us they did. <hi>Sed &amp; juramus ſicut non per genius Caeſarum, it a per ſalutem eorum quae eſt anguſtior om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus geniis:</hi> We do not only pray for the Emperors health, but we alſo ſwear by it, which is a far more ſacred form of oath, then that which you Gentiles uſe, when you ſwear by the Emperours <hi>Genii,</hi> and therefore we refuſe to ſwear in that form, becauſe we Chriſtians know, that they are devils whom you call <hi>Genii;</hi> But yet we ſwear by the health of the Emperour, which is more worth then all the <hi>Genii.</hi> The form of the military oath which Chriſtian Soldiers took even in <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time, is thus laid down in <hi>Vegetius: Per Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtatem Imperatoris quae ſecundum Deum generi humana diligenda eſt &amp; colenda; By the Majeſty of the Emperour, which according to Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance humane kinde ought to love and reverence:</hi> If we would not therefore incurr that guilt, of condemning the generation of the righteous, that have been in all generations, which the man after Gods heart deprecates; we muſt ſubſciibe to this, that in ſuch form; of ſwearing, though we name ſome creature, yer we ſwear not ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately by that creature, but by that God whoſe creature it is: Hence S. <hi>Auſtin Serm.</hi> 28. <hi>in verb. Apoſt. qui per lapidem jurat ſifal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum jurat perjurus eſt, non te audit lapis loquentem, ſed punit Deus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentem. He that ſwears by a ſtone, if he ſwear falſly is perjured, the ſtone</hi> indeed to ſpeak properly <hi>does not hear thee ſpeaking, but God hears thee forſwearing,</hi> and puniſheth thee for thy couſenage, as if the ſtone by which thou ſwaredſt had heard thy words, and reper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts them into the ears of God: alluding to that of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> chap. 24.27. <hi>Behold this ſtone ſhall be a witneſſe unto us, for it hath heard all the words of the Lord which he ſpake unto us,</hi> &amp;c. But what need I call in humane, when we have as plain divine Teſtimony of this Truth as can be expreſt by tongue, given in by Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.21. <hi>Whoſo ſhall ſwear by the temple, ſweareth by it, and by him that dwelleth therein; and he that ſhall ſwear by heaven, ſweareth by the throne of God, and him that ſitteth thereon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. But the Phariſees made ſo great a difference betwixt theſe forms of ſwearing, in point of obliging the conſcience of him that ſwore to a performance of promiſſory, and to ſpeaking the truth in aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory oathes; as to teach that ſwearing in any forme but that which they called <hi>Corban,</hi> or that wherein God was expreſly named
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98333:13"/>did not bring him that took it into an obligation of performance. This ſtrange doctrine of theirs is fully ſtated, and ſubſtantially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.16. <hi>Wo unto you blinde guides, which ſay, whoſoever ſhall ſwear by the temple, it is nothing; but he that ſhall ſwear by the gold of the temple, or by the gift that is on the altar, he is a debtor,</hi> that is, <hi>obliged to pay his vows.</hi> By the gold of the temple they did not mean that wherewith the temple was overlaid (for that was a part of the temple, and as blinde as theſe guides were, they could not be ſuch ſtark-mad fools, as to think ſwearing by a part was more binding then ſwearing by the whole;) but that where with the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-treaſury was endowed, a part being put for the whole; gold, for the gold; ſilver, and other donatives belonging to the ſacred trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, whether they were already brought in thither; or laid up by order of the <hi>Sanhedrin</hi> in other places (as for more ſafety the ſacred pole-money or half-ſhekel, which every <hi>Iſraelite</hi> paid every year for his ſoul, to the uſe of the temple, was in times of war depoſited in ſome ſtrong hold, till a ſufficient convoy could be procured to bring into the ſacred treaſury, either whole or in parcels, as they had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to employ it, either in repairing the temple, or in buying of ſacriſices, <hi>Joſeph. Antiq. l.</hi> 14. <hi>c.</hi> 12.) or but ſo much as was devoted to the temple by vow, though not yet paid into the collectors hands; of which we have a notable inſtance, <hi>Mark</hi> 7.11. <hi>But ye ſay, if a man ſhall ſay to his father or mother, it is Corban, that is to ſay, a gift by whatſoever thou mighteſt be profitod, he is free</hi> from the duty of relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his indigent parents, <hi>and you ſuffer him no more to do ought for his father or mother;</hi> that is, if a mans parents in their neceſſity ſhall ask the honour of maintenance and beg relief of his ſon: if his ſon ſhall ſay, Oh father, that which thou deſireſt me to releive thee with, is a gift, I have conſecrated it by vow to the ſacred treaſury, and am obliged to pay it thither, and therefore cannot without ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perjury divert it to thy maintenance. <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> as he is quoted by <hi>Joſephus</hi> againſt <hi>Appion,</hi> l. 1. makes mention of this Oath, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by <hi>Corban,</hi> or the gift, as ſacred amongſt the Jews, and therefore amongſt other peregrine forms of ſwearing forbid by the laws of the <hi>Tyrians,</hi> door neighbors to the Jews. The Phariſees (I ſay) taught, that <hi>Corban</hi> the gifts of the temple; and gifts upon the altar, were ſo ſacred, as whoſoever did ſwear by them, became thereby a debtor, that is, was obliged to performance; and this was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98333:14"/>the onely form of oath wherein the name of God was not expreſt, which they eſteemed binding: as to all other forms whether by the temple or altar, by heaven or earth, or any creature, in either of them men might bandy them at pleaſure, without the leaſt regret of conſcience, or purpoſe of performing them.</p>
               <p>From this doctrine, their Proſelites were drawn into an opinion that they might call heaven and all therein, ſave God himſelf; earth and all therein ſave <hi>Corban</hi> to bear witneſſe of their ſincerity in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king oath, by their names, and yet ſtill remain as free from obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to perform thoſe oaths, as if they had not ſwore at all, but onely paſt their bare word: and from this opinion into a cuſtome of larding their common diſcourſe wſth all ſuch oathes, as if they had been no more then ornaments of ſpeech, then ſlowers of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick; as if ſwearing by heaven had not implied ſwearing by him that dwells therein. <hi>Jurejurando ſupplentes orationem</hi> (Philo <hi>Jud. de deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logo.</hi>) <hi>quaſi non ſatius eſſe mutilam relinquere. Sceptram non putat eſſe Deos</hi> (as the Poet ſpeaks of a perjur'd King,) He did not think that ſwearing by his ſcepter, was ſwearing by God, who put the ſcepter into his hand: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius</hi> in <hi>Philoſtratus,</hi> l. 6. cenſured <hi>Socrates:</hi>) He did not think that when he ſware by a cock or gooſe, and ſuch creatures, he ſware by their Creator, but did purpoſedly chooſe to ſwear by ſuch things, that he might not bring himſelf under an obligation to keep his oath, as he conceived he muſt have done, if he had ſworn expreſly by God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This being the ſtate of the malady, the great Phyſician of ſouls applys himſelf to the confutation of the opinion which bred and fed it, in the 23. of S. <hi>Matthew,</hi> where herefels that Phariſaical gloſſe, which made void the Law of God: and in the 5. of S. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> he decries the cuſtom of their Proſelites, grounded upon that gloſſe, nay indeed the general cuſtom of the Jews in our Saviours time; for the Phariſees being reputed the Puritans of that time, the ſtricteſt ſect amongſt them, it cannot be otherwiſe deem'd in reaſon, but their doctrine, and the Diſciples practiſe, had a general influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon all that would ſeem nicely religious, and made this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe of common ſwearing, by heaven, earth, temple, or any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but the <hi>Corban,</hi> in a manner Epidemical; and we finde the Scribes and their Scholars, as deep in this mire as the Phariſees; for
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98333:14"/>our Saviour joyns them both together in preaching up this nice di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, betwixt ſwearing by the temple, or altar, and ſwearing by the gifts of the temple, or gifts upon the altar; this laſt form of ſwearing they accounted binding, but the firſt as nothing; to ſwear by the temple they ſaid was nothing, they taught that that was not ſwearing by God, and therefore did not make him that ſwore, a debtor by oath, to the performance of his word. That Epidemical practiſe, I ſay, of ſuch cuſtomary ſwearing by Gods creatures with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect to God (as if this had been no appeal to the Creator, and as it were a pawning of thoſe inviſible things of God, of which the meaneſt of his handiworks bears the impreſſion) which this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine drew after it, is that to which Chriſt adminiſters a remedy in this prohibition, wherein he forbids ſwearing in our ordinary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, by the meaneſt creature (and by conſequence much more by the name of God himſelf, though he mention not that form of ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe the Jewes never ſware by that name but ſolemn oaths.) but not a reverentiall ſwearing when we are lawfully thereunto cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. For the evincing the truth and ſutableneſſe of this, applying Chriſts prohibition to common and not ſolemn ſwearing, I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce arguments taken from thoſe very paſſages in both the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned texts, which the Quakers wreſt to the favoring of their contrary opinion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. That Chriſt prohibits oaths in common ſpeech onely, is manifeſt from the kinde of oath that that law ſpeaks of, which Chriſt cleats from the falſe gloſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.33. out of <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.12. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but ſhalt perform unto the Lord all thy oaths:</hi> For ſwearing by <hi>non</hi>-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of an oath, ſpeaks the oath here mentioned not to be aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory but promiſſory. Now in all Judicatures, the Jews were daily called upon to make aſſertory oaths, touching matter of fact, for the deciſion of controverſies, but as to ſolemn promiſſory oaths (ſuch as <hi>Moſes</hi> adminiſtred when he made all <hi>Iſrael</hi> avouch God for their God; ſuch as <hi>Joſhua</hi> took of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when he made them renounce the Gods of <hi>Canaan</hi> and <hi>Caldea,</hi> and ſwear to ſerve and adhere to the God of <hi>Abraham;</hi> ſuch as ſome religious Kings of <hi>Judch</hi> and <hi>Ezrah</hi> made the Jews take when they ſwore them to the <hi>Covenant</hi>) they were ſo rare and extraordinary, as the laſt of that kinde that we reade of, was that which <hi>Nehemiah</hi> adminiſtred to them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98333:15"/>that had married ſtrange wives, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.25. <hi>I made them ſwear by God, &amp;c.</hi> which was near 400. years before Chriſts Incarnation, and therefore there could not be at the time of Chriſts preaching any one Jew living, who had tranſgreſt the law of God in ſolemn ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a promiſe, and not performing his Oath. Yea the Jewes were by the favour of the <hi>Romans</hi> exempted from taking the military oath, becauſe the taking of it in the gentile form, and the keeping of it in ſome caſes (as marching or fighting on the ſabbath day) was deemed contrary to the law of God. as <hi>Dolobella</hi> writes in his letter to the Epheſians, <hi>Joſeph. Ant.</hi> 14.17. and <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells us, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the like reaſons, the Jewes procured of <hi>Lentulus</hi> a diſmiſſion from the wars. <hi>Religionis ergo eſſe immunes a militia pronunciavi,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Autiq. Jud.</hi> l. 14. c. 17. <hi>I have paſt this ſentence from the tribintall, that the Jewes be exempted from the military oath upon the account of their religion. Dolobella</hi> in his decree of diſcharging the Jewes, pleads the example of the Roman Generalls his predeceſſors. The firſt time that the Roman Emperours fore't the military oath upon the Jewes, was upon occaſion of a vagrant Jew, with his confreers, abuſing the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of <hi>Fulvia</hi> a Roman Matron: near the expiring of the reign of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> and the government of <hi>Pilate,</hi> when the Emperor baniſht them the City, and the Conſulls li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted 4000. of them for the wars; the greateſt part of whom choſe rather to ſuffer death then take the military oath. <hi>Joſeph. Autiq.</hi> l. 18. <hi>c.</hi> 5. Breifly, no people upon earth were more ſcrupulouſly tender of taking ſolemn promiſſory oaths then the Jews were at that time that our Saviour gave them this prohibition, and taxed them for not performing to God their oaths. And therefore to apply Chriſts diſcourſe here to ſuch kinde of oaths, is as prepoſterous as the laying of a plaiſter to the toe when the head is wounded: but the applying of it to their ſtipulations by oath in their private contracts, betwixt man and man, in their common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, and mutuall trading, was ſo proper and ſeaſonable, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be more: for in this caſe they were laviſh of their oaths and regardleſſe of performing them, beyond all humane belief; and if our Saviour had not read the riddle, and told us what ſhifts they had to baſſle the law, and pave their own conſciences, ſo as they could without ſtraining, ſwallow ſuch camel oathes, as <hi>by heaven, by Jeruſalem,</hi> and make no bones, either of taking or keeping them; It could hardly enter into our mindes to conjecture at what door this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98333:15"/>conceit entred into theirs; that thoſe kinde of oaths were not the oaths of God, and therefore did not binde the votaries to pay their vowes unto the Lord, but might be broken without the guilt of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The applying of Chriſts prohibition to ſolemn Oaths, either promiſſory or aſſertory, or to any but common diſcourſe-Oaths, makes Chriſt himſelf a tranſgreſſor of the law; I tremble at the thought of this conſequence which as naturally flows from the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers <hi>hypotheſis,</hi> as light from the ſun: if we conſider at what time Chriſt preacht his ſermon in the Mount, to wit, while that ſacred polity of the Jewes, which God himſelf erected, was yet ſtanding, while thoſe municipall laws under obligation, to which (as well as the ceremonial) Chriſt was born, were yet in force; while <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> was yet the City of the great King, and the Jews under the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of God eſtabliſht by <hi>Moſes</hi> at Gods command; in order to the keeping of peace, and execution of juſtice, wherein God had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Judicatories greater and leſſer, and preſcribed rules for the Judges to walk by in their adminiſtrations, amongſt which this was one, that all controverſies that came before them, ſhould be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the oaths of witneſſes: Had Chriſt therefore at this time prohibited the taking of oaths, in this caſe, it would have been an obſtruction to all legal proceedings, according to that form of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe inſtituted by his Father: It had been the proclaiming of indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to thieves, murderers, blaſphemers, and all ſorts of wicked and injurious perſons, and a turning of hell looſe in that Kingdom of God; for by the ſtanding and yet unrepealed laws of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, queſtions of that nature could not be brought to a determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor malefactors to condign puniſhment without oath. It had been a pragmatical and precocious diſſolution of the whole frame of the divine polity before the time appointed by God, and aſſigned by his propaets, a turning God out of poſſeſſion of his Kingdom of <hi>Judea,</hi> before he had erected his Kingdom in the gentile world, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence an unpeopling all the viſible dominion he had on earth, and leaving him deſtitute of ſubjects. For the veil of the temple was not yet rent with the force of Chriſts expiring breath, the hand-writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Ordinances was not yet cancell'd by the blood of the croſſe, the law either ceremoniall or municipall had not yet loſt its obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging force upon all them that were born under it (as our Saviour
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98333:16"/>was, till by his death he had purchaſt exemption from it and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over it) and therefore had Chriſt or any of his Diſciples been called before the Judicatures to bear witneſſe in a caſe, wherein the civil law of <hi>Moſes</hi> required an oath; they would have thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs obliged in conſcience to have given oath. If he had been made a Judge for the dividing of the inheritance betwixt the two contending brothers, he would in obedience to the law have taken the oaths of witneſſes, if there had been occaſion for it. If he would have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to have determined the caſe of the <hi>woman taken in adultery,</hi> as he askt for the accuſers, <hi>Woman where are thy accuſers?</hi> ſo he would have askt for their witneſſes, and have called the witneſſes to their oaths. Briefly, as they that expound Chriſts prohibition of ſolemn Oaths, do by their refuſing to learn to ſwear <hi>by the Lord,</hi> declare themſelves to be none of Gods people, none of Chriſts Diſciples, but unchriſten themſelves, ſo by faſtning this ſenſe upon our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours words, they un-Chriſt the bleſſed Jeſus, and make him a ſinner in ſtead of a Saviour, ranking him with thoſe falſe Chriſts, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of greater purity, ſought the diſſolution of the civil po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, whoſe ſtories you may ſee in <hi>Joſephus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. After this prohibition, we ſir de S.<hi>Paul,</hi> who received his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, not from man but God, approving of, and appealing to the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of witneſſes, in ſuch Courts, as he knew no evidence would be taken but by Oath, which certainly he would not have done, if he had conceived Chriſt to have forbidden the uſe of ſolemn oaths; when he pleaded his cauſe before <hi>Lyſias,</hi> he appealed to the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the then high-prieſt, <hi>Simon</hi> the ſon of his <hi>quondam</hi> maſter <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> and the whole <hi>Sanhedrin (Joſephus in the hiſtory of his own life)</hi> to bear witneſſe, that he had been educated a Phariſee, and had been a zealous perſecuter of the Church, in going with the <hi>high prieſts</hi> orders &amp; letters at that time that Chriſt appear'd to him; <hi>of all which the high prieſt and all the eſtate of the Elders can boar me witneſs,</hi> Act. 22.5. In his apology before <hi>Felix,</hi> he challengeth his accusers to prove the matters of fact they charged him with, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.13. <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they prove the things whereof they now accuſe me;</hi> he blames them for not bringing up witneſſes (the Jews of <hi>Aſia</hi> who found him in the temple) to alledge if they had ought againſt him, and challengeth all that were then in the Court, to ſay, if they found any evil-doing in him, while he ſtood before the Council, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19, 20. In
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98333:16"/>his anſwer before <hi>Agrippa;</hi> he appeals to the teſtimony of thoſe that knew him from his youth, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.5. <hi>who knew me from the beginning if they would teſtifie:</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> knew very well, that in a matter of life or death (as this was) no evidence would paſſe in Court without oath, and therefore if he had thought ſolemn ſwearing to have been made unlawful by this prohibition of Chriſt, he would rather have undergone a thouſand deaths then tempt ſo many to make ſhipwrack of their immortal ſouls, by calling them to that unlawful act.</p>
               <p n="4">4. None of thoſe forms of ſwearing mentioned here by Chriſt, nor any of like nature, would paſſe for current or legal before a Jewiſh Magiſtrate, but only ſuch forms, as wherein the Name of God was invok't expreſly. The Law was ſo clear, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſwear by the Lord thy God,</hi> as whoever ſhould in any Court of Judicature tender any other form of oath, that form might have been excepted againſt by him againſt whom it was given, as inſufficient, to end the controverſie depending, as void in their Judaical law, which being of divine inſtitution, it was not within the verge of humane power, either to diſpence with, or alter the forms of proceeding therein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt. From this cuſtom of the Jews in open Court, to ſwear by no other name, but that of God, the maker of heaven and earth, and ſea, <hi>Appion</hi> accuſed the Jews of ſingularity, as hereby diſcrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves from all other Nations, who did not ſo ſtrictly tic up themſelves to that form of ſwearing in their Judicatorles, <hi>Joſeph. l.</hi> 2. <hi>in Appion. Philo Judaeus</hi> in his Allegories of the Law, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth all them accurſed that ſay, they ſwear by God; but 'tis u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual for the wiſeſt Jewiſh Scribes to run beyond their wits, in alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorizing the Law, becauſe they do not look to Chriſt the end of it; Howbeit he recovers himſelf, in his treatiſe of the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> where ſpeaking of ſolemn ſwearing before a Judge in a caſe of controverſy, he defines it, a citation of God, to bear witneſs in doubtful caſes and aggravates the ſin of perjury in that caſe, from the infamy which it caſts upon his name. And in his Treatiſe of ſpeciall laws, where he adviſeth, that when the neceſſity of the thing required an oath, men would not preſently have recourſe to God himſelf, but uſe ſome other form, and rather call in ſome of Gods creatures to be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, doth give ſufficient hints, that he ſpeaks there of elective oaths onely, which men uſe in private, and not ſuch as men are called to take in the courſe of law; and therefore puts in this <hi>proviſo,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98333:17"/>Salvis legibus,</hi> when the law allows thee another form, that is, in thy ordinary communication, manifeſtly implying, that no form was good in law, but that wherein God himſelf was named for a witneſſe. And indeed both Judge and litigants muſt have been out of their wits, if they had laid the deciſion of controverſy upon ſuch oaths as were prae-declared to be of no validity, as theſe forms were which Chirſt prohibits. Briefly, the Jews were accouſtomed in their mutuall converſe only, and not ſolemnly before the magiſtrate, to ſwear by the heaven and earth, Therefore this prohibition of Chriſt reacheth only elective, and not ſolemn and neceſſary oaths.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The reaſon which Chriſt annexeth to his prohibition, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixeth to his command, <hi>that our word ſhould be yea and nay,</hi> is an evidence that Chriſt here ſpeaks of common diſcourſe, <hi>ſwear not by heaven, for it is Gods throne,</hi> &amp;c. As if he ſhould have ſaid, the reaſon why ſuch like oaths, are ſo common in your mouths, is this conceit, that you ſwear not by God in the uſe of ſuch forms, and therefore are not obliged by them any more then by your bare word. But I tell you that heaven is Gods throne, and therefore he that ſweareth by that, ſweareth by him that ſitteth thereon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nay, your head and every hair that grows thereon is Gods creature, and he that ſwears by that, appeals to its maker: you cite God to bear witneſſe every time you uſe ſuch oaths, and God is not lightly, and upon every ſlight occaſion in mens common ſpeech, to be ſummoned in to bear witneſſe, as the Phariſies themſelves confeſſe, in their avoiding ſuch oaths in their oreinary communication, as they think are appeals un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. And therefore now you have learnd that in ſwearing by the creature, men ſwear alſo by the Creatour; as you would not be ſound guilty of taking his name in vain, diſuſe your tongues in your common talk from ſuch forms, and let your ordinary word be <hi>yea or nay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. The motive that S.<hi>James</hi> urgeth, argueth that 'tis common ſwearing that he prohibits, <hi>leſt ye fall into condemnation,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or according to other Copies, <hi>leſt ye fall into hyyocriſie,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. If we follow the firſt reading, the emphaſis, will lie in the verb <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whence comes our Engliſh (with a little variation, to trip or unawares ſtumble; leſt unexpectedly ye fall flat into the guilt of perjury, and while you dream not of it, become obnxious to that damnatfon, which is the wages of taking
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98333:17"/>Gods Name in vain: For while you fancy, that ſo long as you uſe not Gods Name, but only ſwear <hi>by heaven and earth,</hi> it is nothing, (when in very deed he that ſwears by heaven, ſwears alſo by him that dwells therein) you precipitate your ſelves hoodwinkt into the abyſſe of perjury, every time you call any of Gods creatures to witneſſe to a falſity, and he that upon ſuch grounds as the Scribes and Phariſees have laid, inures himſelf to common ſwearing, cannot be in extreme peril of ſetting Gods ſeal unwittingly to many an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth; If we follow the other reading, <hi>leſt ye fall into hypocriſie,</hi> which with <hi>Grotius, H. Stephen,</hi> and others, I rather incline to; (It's more likely that an haſty Scribe might overſlip [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] and he that ſhould reade the Copy after him divide <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to make it ſenſe, into <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, then that any ſhould have the boldneſſe to inſert it.) It will bear more reſemblance to Chriſts Diſcourſe about the Phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal mode of ſwearing, for which he calls them hypocrites, and for teaching, that men might uſe ſuch forms without laying thereby the leaſt obligation upon themſelves to perform their promiſes. Now as this doctrine betrayed their Profelites to a cuſtomary uſe of oaths, ſo by that cuſtome they contracted an habit of lying, even then when they ſeemed to be moſt ſerious, and to give their words the greateſt conſirmation: So that in effect their whole communication was a conſtant trade of hypocriſie and diſſimulation. And while they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended one thing (to give aſſurance by oath that they would fulfill their promiſe) and yet intended another (to lay no obligation upon themſelves) by that kinde of oath, what was this but to play the knave under the vizor of an honeſt man?</p>
               <p n="7">7. No leſſe plain Teſtimony to this truth, doth S. <hi>James</hi> his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to this prohibition adminiſter, <hi>But above all things my brethren ſwear not,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is no where elſe in all the Scriptute rendred <hi>[above]</hi> but <hi>[before]</hi> and it ſhould be ſo rendred here: For the Apoſtle doth not by this phraſe denote the priority of dignity of this caution (as if he would have us eſteem more highly of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept then of all the reſt; for he commands ſeveral things of equal, if not more importance, and which it concerns us as much to obſerve whether we weigh the conſiderableneſſe of the duties, or the prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of men to be negligent in the obſervance of them.) <hi>Quid eſt ante omnia nolite jurare? jurare enim pejus eſt quam furari? quam adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terari? non dico falſum jurare: Jurare dico; Jurare pejus eſt quam ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98333:18"/>occidere? abſit, hominem occidere furari adulterari peccatum eſt, jur are non eſt peccatum,</hi> Auguſt. <hi>Serm.</hi> 28. <hi>de verb. Apoſtoli, c.</hi> 8. what means this, <hi>above all things ſwear not?</hi> Is ſwearing (forſooth) worſe then adultery? I ſay not, is falſe-ſwearing? but Is ſwearing? It ſwearing I ſay worſe then man ſlaughter? God forbid! what meant then this, above or before all things? <hi>iſto verbo cautus nos facit adverſus linguam noſtram, ſi de manu aliquid faceres, facilius manui tui impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rares ne faceret; lingua facilitatem habet motus, in udo poſita eſt, facilt in lubrico labitur,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> reſolves in the ſame Sermon: By this caution the Apoſtle would have us ſet a watch upon our tongue; If thou wert bid to with-hold thy hand, thou mighteſt more eaſily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that; the tongue is nimble and quick in motion, it is plac't in a watry Element, it ſtands on a ſlippery place, and eaſily lapſeth; But yet it is as apt to lie, ſlander, and calumniate, as to ſwear: This form of ſpeech therefore doth moſt properly import priority of place and time in our communication, which the Apoſtle would not have us aſſigne to ſwearing; as if he had ſaid, Now that I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you to patience by the example of the Husbandman, of the Prophets, of <hi>Job, &amp;c. verſ. 7,</hi> 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let me give you this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that you would take heed of humouring the impatience of your ſpirit by permitting it to hurry you forthwith to ſwearing upon every provocation, though it be but by ſuch petty Oaths, as the Phariſees have taught you; Let not an Oath lie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt upon your heart, and come firſt of all before all things out of your mouth; Try all other ways of ſatisfying thoſe with whom you converſe, of the truth of your ſpeeches, before you atteſt it by Oath: <hi>quantam ad me pertinet juro, ſed quantum mihi videtur magna neceſſitate compulſus; Cum videro non mihi credi niſi faciam, &amp; ei qui mihi non credit non expedire quod non credit,</hi> &amp;c. As for my own part I ſometimes ſwear, (but ſo far as I am able to judge) not but when I am compell'd with the greateſt neceſſity, when I ſee that I cannot be believed except I ſwear, and that it ſtands not with my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours good, that he does not believe me, <hi>Id ibid.</hi> An oath is the greateſt bond of fidelity amongſt men, and therfore we ſhould have recourſe to it as our ſacred anchor, when nothing elſe will eſtabliſh men in the truth of what we ſay; <hi>That faith which we make by oath is the moſt perfect that can be given,</hi> ſaith <hi>Halicarnaſſenſis. The moſt firm, and therefore ſhould be the laſt pawn of our veracity,</hi> ſaith <hi>Procopius
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98333:18"/>Perſicorum,</hi> l. 2. But does it follow, that becauſe we muſt not ſwear at all, not by any kinde of oath, firſt of all, or before all other wayes of procaring credit to our words, that therefore we may at the laſt extremity have recourſe to a ſolemn Oath.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The argument that our Saviour urgeth to perſwade us, that we ſwear not at all, but let our communication be <hi>yea, yea; nay, nay;</hi> evinceth Chriſt to intend in this prohibition, common, but not ſolemn ſwearing. <hi>For whatſoever is more then theſe cometh of evill,</hi> or, <hi>the evill one,</hi> that is, <hi>of the devil.</hi> For except we underſtand Chriſt to ſpeak here of ſuch voluntary aſſeverations as men make in their ordinary diſcourſe, and not of ſuch as either the weight of the caſe, or the neceſſity of juſtice call for; we muſt be conſtrain'd impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to aſſert, that in all thoſe paſſages prae-alledged in S. <hi>Paul,</hi> where he called God to witneſſe, came from an evill ſpirit; that our bleſſed Saviour ſo often as he ſaid, <hi>amen, amen,</hi> which is more then <hi>yea, yea;</hi> had thoſe words put into his mouth by the evill one; that the elect Angell which Chriſt ſent from heaven to communicate the knowledge of future things to S. <hi>John,</hi> was inſpired by the devill, when we ſwear <hi>by him that liveth for ever.</hi> Is it a hard matter now to chooſe, whether we ſhould think, that the choſen veſſel, the elect Angel, yea, the Archangell of the Covenant, were led by an evill ſpirt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſay more then yea, yea; nay, nay; Or that thoſe men are led by a ſpirit of errour, and under Judiciall blindeneſſe, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee, that the words of Chriſt muſt neceſſarily be referred to vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantary raſh oaths, in our common diſcourſe, upon ſlieght occaſion, without reverence of the divine Majeſtie, or intention to ratifie ſome truth or promiſe of weight? But that which will give a clearer light to this text, and be a more full demonſtration of the truth that I am contending for, is this obſervation.</p>
               <p>That Chriſt affirms whatſoever is more then theſe, in the caſe wherein he prohibits the uſe of more to be intrinſecally, and of its own nature, of an evill originall. For he does not ground this poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>[whatſoever is more, is of evill]</hi> upon either his prohibition or command; As if his meaning were, that 'tis therefore evill becauſe he hath now forbid the uſe of more; but on the contrary, he grounds both his prohibition <hi>[Swear not]</hi> and his injunction [<hi>let your commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication,</hi> &amp;c.] upon this argument, becauſe <hi>whatſoever is more then theſe, is of evill:</hi> and preſſeth the intrinſecal evil, that is naturally, in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98333:19"/>that which he prohibits, (antecedently to his forbidding of it,) as the reaſon of his prohibition. He does not ſay, I have now forbid you to ſwear, or to uſe any more then <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>nay,</hi> and therefore the uſe of more is evill; But, the uſe of more in the caſe that I ſpeak of, is evil, and therefore I probibit it: whence it unavoidably follows, that in all caſes wherein Chriſt here forbids ſwearing, it was ever a ſin to ſwear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a ſin in the Patriarchs, and Old-Teſtament. Saints, before this prohibition, as well as it is in us Chriſtians ſince; that is, raſhly, prophanely, irreverently, in our ordinary commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication: and that Chriſt hath not made that kinde of reverent ſwearing a ſin to Chriſtians, that was the duty and commendation of his antient people.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is manifeſt, that all raſh ſwearing, whether in Jew or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, proceeds from the evill heart of him that inures himſelf to it; from that pride, athieſm, and hypocriſy that lodgeth in the breaſt, doth the mouth utter all vain, fruitleſſe, and precipitate oaths and aſſeverations; and therefore, he that fears God, will abſtain from all cuſtomary oaths, not only for fear of the event (<hi>ne jurando ad fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitatem jurandi veniatur ex facilitate ad conſuetudinem ex con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine in perjurium decidatur,</hi> S. Auſtin <hi>de mend.</hi> c. 15. <hi>leſt by ſwearing</hi> we contract a facility to ſwear, and fall from a facility to a cuſtom; and from cuſtome into perjury,) but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to that evill fountain, (the prophaneneſſe of the ſwearers hearts) whence all ſuch ſlink calves of the lips are caſt. In a word, the <hi>Ruſſian</hi> diſgorgeth oaths from the ſame Principle, that the Fanatick powreth out <hi>extempore</hi> prayers, neither of them conſider, that they are before God, while they invoke his name, and therefore they are ſo ready to offer the ſacrifice of fools. As there are certain forms of words, at the uſing whereof, evill ſpirits, (by vertue of diabolicall inſtitution) preſent themſelves, ſo all forms of invoking God, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Oath or prayer, exhibit the divine preſence to us, of which preſence, if they had regard, the one would not think it nothing to ſwear, nor the other to pray unadviſedly; neither of them would be ſo haſty with their mouths, ſo haſty to utter, <hi>quicquid in buccam,</hi> if they did conſider they were before God. My ranking them together will diſpleaſe them both, but let them wreak their ſpleen upon <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> who hath coupled them as brethren in iniquity, as alike-guilty of Athieſtical prophaneſſe, and hath preſcribed the ſame method of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98333:19"/>cure for them both, if they have wit or grace to apply themſelves to the obſervation of his rules. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And it is as manifeſt from the Inſtances of Chriſt and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that more then theſe ſometimes, and in ſome caſes, proceeds from good, from a divine principle, from an honeſt and gracious heart, to wit, when ſtrong aſſeverations even by oath are uſed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Reverentially, as a ſolemn invocation of Gods name, as the celebration of the higheſt and moſt auguſt act of divine worſhip and adoration that can poſſiblie be tendred to the divine majeſty.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Deliberately, with due conſideration and preponderation of the weight of the thing, the importance of our Neighbours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving it, the probability that he will be prevail'd to beleeve us, upon the interpoſition and aſſurance of the oath, <hi>&amp;c. Et ideo non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venitur juraſſe niſi ſcribens ubi conſideratio cautior non habet linguam praecipitem.</hi> We do not finde, (ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin de mend.</hi> c. 15.) that S. <hi>Paul</hi> did ſwear, but when he was writing, becauſe the pen is not ſo great a blabb as the tongue; men are more circumſpect of the words that fall from their quill then of them that drop from their lipps.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Sincerely, with a purpoſe to lay as great an Obligation upon thy ſelf to keep thy promiſe, and ſwear truly, as thy making oath imports to thy neighbour, when thy minde and words are both of a colour, and the impreſſions of thy ſoul correſpond with the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of thy mouth; when thy conſcience can tell thee that thou ſpeakeſt before God in thy heart what thou uttereſt to thy neighbour in words.</p>
               <p>All theſe conditions concur'd in our Saviours and S. <hi>Pauls</hi> aſſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and therefore though they were more then theſe, yet they proceeded not of evill, but from a good and honeſt heart, and were all wanting in thoſe Phariſaicall oaths which our Saviour condemns, wherein they had neither reverentiall thoughts of God (for they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived they did by thoſe forms ſwear by God) nor weighed the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ponderated circumſtances, but upon every ſlieght, upon no occaſion bolted out fruitleſs oaths: nor did they intend to binde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to a performance of their word, for they accounted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as free after ſuch oaths as if they had never made them. Such kinde of additions to our yea and nay, are of themſelves evil, and thereſore forbidden; But the ground and reaſon of Chriſts prohibition
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98333:20"/>does not reach the other ſort of additions.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That I may make the two Teſtaments kiſſe one another at part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and bring the ends of my diſcourſe together, Let it be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the propheſies before-quoted, That to interpret thoſe Evangolical texts as prohibitions to Chriſtians to ſwear in any caſe, draws after it theſe blaſphemous conſequences.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Chriſt who came to accompliſh and ſeal propheſies, to full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill what was ſpoken by the mouth of the prophets, which have been ſince the world began, did contradict by his precepts and prohibit the accompliſhment of thoſe propheſies, that foretold, that under the Goſpel, when Gods name ſhould be great in all the earth, his elect and choſen ſervants ſhould ſwear by the God of truth, as an evidence of their converſion to him from idols.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That S. <hi>James</hi> was by the Holy Ghoſt (which Chriſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhould <hi>leade his Apoſtles-into all truth</hi>) to forbid that, (<hi>viz.</hi> to learn to ſwear after the way of Gods people <hi>the Lord liveth</hi>) under pain of falling into condemnation, or at leaſt into hypocriſy; which the Spirit of Chriſt in the holy Prophets perſwades Chriſtians to do, under pain of utter deſtruction, in caſe of neglect, and by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of being built up in the midſts of Gods people, in caſe they would dilligently, <hi>learn to ſwear by his name:</hi> which the ſame ſpirit commends to Chriſtians as a ſigne of their ſincere and cordiall accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the true God for their God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That if the Chriſtian Church does not perform homage to the God of truth by ſwearing as well as bleſſing in his name; If their tongue does not as well ſwear as their knees bow to him, then the Chriſtian people are not the people of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> the <hi>Meſſias</hi> is not yet come, but ſtill to be expected; then the bleſſed Jeſus is not that Chriſt of whom the prophets ſpeak, but as the Jews at his arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and their poſterity blaſphemouſly ſtile him, a deceiver, and a counterfeit; For by the prophets it was foretold, that at his exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and vocation of the gentiles to the knowledge of the true God, the gentiles called by his name ſhould ſwear by the God of truth, throughout the earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yield but this much to a Jew or Pagan, that the Chriſtian law forbids worſhipping of God, by ſwearing by his name, forbids any other confirmation of what we affirm but <hi>yea yea, nay nay;</hi> and you do not only deprive the Chriſtian Cauſe and Church of one of her ſtrongeſt bulwarks, of one of thoſe demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98333:20"/>of the ſpirit (<hi>the ſpirit of propheſy in the holy men of old,</hi> whereby the Champions of the Chriſtian faith have inrefragably proved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all aſſailants, that Jeſus is the prophets Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe ſince his calling of us gentiles by his goſpell, we have worſhipt the true God by ſwearing by his name; but alſo adminiſter to Inſidells an unanſwerable argument for them to prove, that that Jeſus whom we Chriſtians worſhip for the Chriſt, is not indeed the very Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe he hath forbid that worſhip to be exhibited, which the prophets foretold men ſhould learn to tender the God of truth, at the coming of that Chriſt, whom they ſpeak of. It is not poſſible to imagine any thing more unlike, or oppoſite to one another, then that Chriſt and his diſciples, which the prophets deſcribe, are, to what this gloſſe of the Quakers preſents Jeſus Chriſt and his diſciples to be. In the reign of the Prophets Chriſt, Gods choſen ones of the Gentiles are to do him homage, to acknowledge their ſubjection to him, dependance on him, awe of him, and his dreadfull attributes, by <hi>ſwearing by his name;</hi> But in the reign of the Quakers Chriſt, the world indeed may take its own courſe, but they whom God hath called and choſen out of the world, are not to ſwear at all. The people of the Prophets Chriſt, at what time he ſhould publiſh his royall law, and men ſhould be taught of God, wore to learn to ſwear, <hi>the Lord liveth,</hi> and to be made to ply this leſſon with a promiſe <hi>to be built up, if they learn'd it diligently,</hi> with a threat, <hi>to be plucked up,</hi> if they did not, But the people of the Quakers Chriſt, are taught of God, that they muſt not learn this leſſon, and are terrified from their book with clamours againſt it, as evill, as leading to deſtruction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For the oppoſition is ſo palpable, as I need not illuſtrate it with more Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. It can now therefore be a matter of no great difficulty to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, whether expoſition and practiſe, grounded upon theſe expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, is more juſtifiable. That of the Chriſtian Church in all ages which ſo expounds Chriſts words, as not prohibiting her to give to God the honour that's due to him, by a reverentiall invocating of his great name, in ſacred and ſolemn oaths, to the end that the ſayings of the prophets may be fulfill'd, &amp; our Jeſus demonſtrated to be the Chriſt; or that of the Quakers whoſe gloſſe defrauds God of his due homage, robs the King of Saints of one of the prime Jewells of his crown, preſents the ever-bleſſed Jeſus in the form of an Impoſtor and falſe Chriſt, leads directly to the gulf of groſſeſt inſidelity and denial
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98333:21"/>of Chriſt; and ſets the Old and New-Teſtaments, the Prophets and Evangeliſts at greater odds, then the <hi>Manichaeans</hi> did; making the Goſpel to contradict thoſe holy Prophets, to whoſe teſtimony our Saviour conſtantly appeal'd, for the deciſion of that great queſtion, whether he was that Chriſt that was to come? putting it to this iſſue, that he would forego the claim, and give them leave to call him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver; if he did not exactly anſwer that model, which the Prophets had drawn of him that was to come; if they could diſcern one line in the whole body of his perſon, of his doctrine, of his followers, diſproportionable to thoſe features with which the penſil of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets had painted the <hi>Meſſias, John</hi> 5.39, 46. and <hi>John</hi> 10.37. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.4. All that our Saviour did, all he ſuffered, all he taught, was by rule of propheſie, doing, ſuffering, teaching no other things then what the Prophets ſaid he ſhould, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.22. and therefore that muſt needs be an unclean beaſt that does not divide the hoof, that is, that interpretation of any Evangelical Text, is bancful to the ſoul that is not ſupported by the Prophetical as well as Apoſtolical Writings; much more that which goeth and puſheth at the Prophets, with ſo manifeſt a contradiction as that doth, which interprets Chriſt to forbid his Diſciples to do, what the prophets ſay, he ſhould teach his Diſciples to learn, to wit, to ſwear <hi>the Lord liveth,</hi> to ſpeak the language of <hi>Canaan</hi> in ſwearing to him, to confeſſe unto him by <hi>ſwearing by his Name;</hi> The performance of which homage to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, that it might be more auguſt, reverential, obligatory to the Votaries, and ſatisfactory to all in point of an indubitable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of controverſie; It is and always was the will of God, that Oaths ſhould be reſerv'd and ſequeſtred to the ſervice of God, and the publick weal of mankinde, and not ſquandred away in our ordinary converſe; which will of the holy God, when the Scribes and Phariſees had made void by their Traditional gloſſes, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our vindicates, and reſtores to its primitive luſtre, by wiping off that duſt, and renewing this prohibition, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> (that is, in your common talk) not ſo much as by heaven or earth, or an hair of your head, but let your common word be <hi>yea yea, nay nay.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:98333:21"/>
               <head>SECTION III.</head>
               <p>WHen I had blown off the duſt, of falſe gloſſes from thoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Texts, which the Quakers pervert to the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the univerſal practiſe of the Church of Chriſt, I hoped I had done enough to the Vindication of this part of divine worſhip, and to the ur deceiving of that deluded party; But their ſtating the caſe, relating to Oaths and ſwearing, and preſenting it to the ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the King and both Houſes of Parliament, ſpeaks them ambitions to be thought to have better company in their way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding Chriſt and Saint <hi>James,</hi> then I am ſure ever ſet foot in it, or caſt an eye towards it (except it was aſquint) even Primitive Chriſtians, Martyrs, and Fathers, who were (as they ſay) of the ſame minde and judgement with them. It will be requiſite therefore that I demonſtrate the impertinency of thoſe Examples which they alledge, and the want of either ingenuity or honeſty that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray in making of them.</p>
               <div n="1" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Policarp</hi> being demanded to ſwear by the Emperours good fortune or <hi>Caeſars</hi> proſperity, denied, ſaying, <hi>he was a Chriſtian,</hi> and ſo was committed to the flames becauſe he would not ſwear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>It is a bad <hi>omen</hi> when men ſtumble on the threſhold, as they do here in this firſt Example, in their alledging whereof they commit more palpable errours then there are ſentences.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Whereas they interprot <hi>[good fortune]</hi> by proſperity, as if the: Preconſul had required no more of him but to ſwear by <hi>Caeſars</hi> proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity: <hi>Euſebius</hi> in the place quoted, hath [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] which his Tranſlator renders, <hi>Jura per Caeſaris genium,</hi> ſwear by the <hi>genius,</hi> the good <hi>deamon,</hi> or good fortune of <hi>Caeſar;</hi> which form of oath <hi>Policarp</hi> and the whole Army of Martyrs refuſed to take, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that which the Gentiles ſtiled <hi>genii,</hi> the Chriſtians knew to be devils, which were worſhipped under the names of good Angels; as hath been allready obſerv'd out of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and every ſchool-boy conſtrue that verſe, <hi>Te facimus fortuna deam coeloque lecainus;</hi> we make thee a Goddeſſe of fortune (which is the engliſh of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) and place thee in heaven, a doughty argument: <hi>Policarp</hi> would not ſwear
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98333:22"/>by an heatheniſh goddeſſe, or their Gods, who were devils, and therefore Chriſtians muſt not ſwear by the true God, when the quite contrary follows: For God would not grudge idols that honour, if it were not his own peculiar.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Their comparing the oath which the Preconſul tendred to <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carp,</hi> to that form of oath which is in uſe in this kingdom, as they manifeſtly do, in that parentheſis <hi>[which was then their nationall oath]</hi> aſperſeth the King and both Houſes of Parliament with the crime of heatheniſh idolatry.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Their expounding the Preconful his ſpeach <hi>[take thine oath and I will diſcharge thee]</hi> defie Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>ſwear not,</hi> as if <hi>Policarp</hi> had refuſed to ſwear upon the account of Chriſts prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not upon the account of the impiety of the form of the oath it ſelf; or as if to ſwear at all, though by the true God, had been to defie Chriſt; or as if ſwearing and refuſing to ſwear at all, had then been the mark of diſtinction betwixt heathens and Chriſtians: when indeed the true criterion was this, that the gentiles would have had the martyrs ſwear by the idols, but the martyrs would not ſwear but by the God of truth: theſe I ſay are moſt manifeſt perverſions of the texts both of <hi>Euſebius</hi> and M. <hi>Fox.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pontius</hi> and <hi>Blondina</hi> refuſed to ſwear, being often urged, <hi>Euſeb,</hi> l. 5. cap. 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>It ſhould be <hi>cap.</hi> 1 where <hi>Euſebius</hi> reports their Martyrdom, and gives this reaſon why they would not ſwear, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rgebanturque per gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilium idola jurare, they were urged to ſwear by the Idols of the Gentiles.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>3.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Baſilides</hi> a Souldier, being required to give an oath in a matter concerning his fellow-ſouldiers, denied to do it, plainly affirming he was a Chriſtian, <hi>Euſeb.</hi> l. 6. cap. 5. for I muſt make hold to ſet down the book which they have omitted, <hi>Fox</hi> vol. 1. fol. 71.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Euſebius</hi> his words are, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>cum a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militonibus ſuis Sacramento adigerctur;</hi> being urged by his fellow-ſouldiers to take the Military oath, which was wont then to be by the Idols and the Emperours, ſaith M. <hi>Fox</hi> in the place quoted. I do not remember that ever I met with ſo many authoritles together ſo wickedly falſified, as theſe are.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="example">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:98333:22"/>
                  <head>Example <hi>4.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In the Plowmans Complaint is this, <hi>viz. Lord, thou giveſt us a commandment of truth, in bidding us ſay, yea yea, nay nay, and ſwear for nothing; but Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>This I confeſſe comes home to the point, if the allegation be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but if this Plowman be <hi>Chaucers Jack <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pland,</hi> (as by his ſtile he ſeems to be) I never read that he was Canonized a Martyr, or dub'd a Father of the Church, though he be the dad of Engliſh Poets; nor do I think his Romance will paſſe amongſt rationall men for good authority.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>5.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John Wicliff</hi> was condemned for holding forth, that <hi>all Oaths which be made for any comtract or bargain betwixt man and man, were unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> Fox <hi>vol.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 387.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>This was indeed the 41. Article charged againſt him; but what is this to ſolemn ſwearing when we are lawfully called to it?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>William Swinderley,</hi> the 14. Article againſt him was, that he ſhould ſay, <hi>that no man ought to ſwear for any thing, but ſimply without an oath to affirm or deny.</hi> Fox <hi>vol.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 614.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>The Anſwer which (in the place quoted) he returned: to that charge, ſhall be mine; <hi>Oft</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>have I ſaid, and yet will, that men ſhould not ſwear by any creature, and that no man ſhould ſwear in idle, as well nigh all people uſeth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>7.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Theſe general received doctrines by the poor Chriſtians in this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was, that <hi>neither Pope, nor Prelate, nor-Ordinary, can compell any to ſwear by any creature of God, or by the bible-book.</hi> Fox. <hi>vol</hi> 1. <hi>fol:</hi> 687.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>Both poor and rich Chriſtians of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> do retain the ſame doctrine at this day, and when either Pope, Prelate, or Ordinary, impoſe any other form of oath upon you but what is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht by law, and wherein you are urged to ſwear, not by any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but by God, Creator, and Redeemer, you may complain and be relieved.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="example">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:98333:23"/>
                  <head>Example <hi>8.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>William Thorpe,</hi> when <hi>Tho. Arundel</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> bid him lay his hand upon the book that he might ſwear thereby, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>Sir, A book is nothing elſe but a thing coupled together of many creatures, and to ſwear by any creature, both Gods Law and mans is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</hi> One Article againſt him was, that he preacht in S.<hi>Chads</hi> Church in <hi>Shrewsbury, that it is not lawfull to ſwear in any caſe.</hi> Fox. <hi>vol.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 689.690.692.701.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>It was ingeniouſly anſwered, and pat to the Archbiſhops urging him to ſwear (not as the law ordains upon) but by the book. But yet withal, that holy Martyr in the place quoted hath theſe words. <hi>[Sir, this thing I ſay here, before theſe your Clerks, that how, where, when, and to whom men are bound to ſwear, I will, through Gods grace, be ever ready thereto.]</hi> And as to the Article, he denied that ever he Preacht any ſuch doctrine, either at <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> or any where elſe, but only, that by S. <hi>James</hi> his authority, it is not lawfull to ſwear by any creature; nor in any caſe, where the taking of an oath could be excuſed to them, that have power to impoſe an oath. In which point I cordially concurr with him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Elizabeth Young, Anno.</hi> 1558. refuſed to ſwear, and perſiſted in that refuſal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Fox. <hi>vol.</hi> 3. f. 910.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>One of the oaths that was tendred her, was, what books ſhe had ſold, this ſhe refuſed to take, becauſe ſhe would not betray her Chriſtian friends; and the other oath they would have had her make was, whether ſhe was a man or woman? this ſhe refuſed, becauſe that might be determined without an oath, to wit, by being ſearcht by women, and therefore ſhe offer'd her ſelf to be ſearcht, denying to give them any other ſatisfaction but that, and her bare affirming her ſelf to be a woman, becauſe what was more then that, in that caſe, was of evill. <hi>Fox</hi> in the place quoted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>10.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The <hi>Waldenſes</hi> profeſſed it to be no way lawfull for a Chriſtian to ſwear, whoſe defenſe Biſhop <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> undertakes, <hi>De ſucceſſ.</hi> cap. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>11.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>One Article urged againſt the Proteſtants of <hi>Piedmont, Anno</hi> 1655.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98333:23"/>was, that they believed, it was not lawfull to ſwear any thing. <hi>Morland, hiſt.</hi> pa. 217.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>I joyn theſe, becauſe they of <hi>Piedmont</hi> are the Relicts of the old <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> againſt whom this was wont to be charged by the Papiſts, that they were wholy againſt all ſwearing. In which point the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Armagh</hi> undertakes to vindicate them: but how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not by maintaining the opinion, but, by proving it to be a calumny caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them by their adverſaries. <hi>Frater Nicolaus Eymericus,</hi> 2. <hi>part. derect. inquiſitor. Haereſis</hi> Waldenſium, <hi>tertia dicitun quod jurare in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio, ſive extra judicium, in quacunquo cauſa, est illicitum &amp; mort ale peccatum quartus eorum error est, quod dej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>are in judicio coram judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus ale dicenda veritate &amp; revelandis complicibus ſuis in hae ſecta, non est illicitum &amp; peccatam, imolicitum &amp; ſanctum.</hi> Friar <hi>Nicelus Eyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus</hi> (in the ſecond part of his directions to the Inquiſitors,) reckons this to be the 3d hereſie of the <hi>Waldenſes;</hi> That to ſwear, whether it be before a Judge or <hi>extra</hi>-judicially, in any caſe, is unlawfull, and a mortall ſin. Their fourth errour is. That to ſwear-falſly before a Judge in open Court, when the Queſtion is about confeſſing truth, or revealing their Complices and fellow-Sectarians, is not unlawfull or a ſin, but lawfull and ſacred. This Biſhop <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> relates in the place fore-quoted, <hi>pag.</hi> 162. on purpoſe to evince the ſlanderous pens of Roman Scribes, from the incoherency of their calumnies, and from the extream unlikelihood that they who held it lawfull (in ſome caſes) to forſwear, ſhould hold it unlawfull (in any caſe) to ſwear. If you did not ſee this to be the defence which that learned Primat made, where are you eyes? if you did, where is your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? and where do you think muſt be our wit, if we believe thoſe men upon their bare word, who belie ſo many Authours in writing?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>12.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Eraſmus, Plato, Meander, Antonius, Heſiod, Theognis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>This rancking <hi>Eraſmus</hi> with heathens, ſmells rank of the Jeſuits ſpirit, whoſe deviſe it is to paint him hanging betwixt heaven and hell, as being neither Papiſt nor Proteſtant, in their verdict, and by conſequence either a Mahometan or Pagan. But whatever his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was, as to Papiſts or Proteſtants, it was farr enough from the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98333:24"/>opinion of the Quakers; for where he ſpeaks of the unlawfulneſſe of ſwearing, of the uſeleſſneſſe of oaths, he ſpeaks of ſwearing in our ordinary communication, as is manifeſt from that clauſe <hi>[In your bargains,]</hi> ye need no oath, ye need no execration, which the Quaker Apologiſt either ignorantly or maliciouſly omits. I appeal to the place by him quoted, (his Annotations on <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34) As to the reſt of thoſe authorities that are joynd with his, they are anſwered (<hi>Sect.</hi> 1. <hi>Argum.</hi> 1.) where S. <hi>Pauls</hi> practiſe is oppoſed to them which ought to be of more weight with Chriſtians then all the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of all heathen Poets and Philoſophers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>13.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 88. It is well that God hath forbidden men to ſwear, leſt by cuſtom of ſwearing, <hi>&amp;c. de mondacio.</hi> leſt by ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ye come to a cuſtome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>The very words here alledged, evince, that S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks of common ſwearing, and certainly he muſt be beſide his Text, if from the Old Teſtament he infer the unlawfulneſs of all kinde of ſwearing; what his judgement is about oaths, in his Treatiſe <hi>de mendacio,</hi> hath been already declared.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14-15" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>14.</hi> and <hi>15.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The <hi>Albines</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Michael Sadler</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>Your Authours ſay only, that that charge was alledged againſt them, but not that it was proved.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16-18" type="example">
                  <head>Example <hi>16, 17, 18.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Jerome, Chryſoſtom, Juſtin Martyr, Walter Brute.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>When you name the Texts of theſe three Fathers, we ſhall exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether you faithfully report them: As to <hi>Walter Brute,</hi> It is true, he affirmed what is alledged, but with proteſtation, that he would retract that opinion, if he were convine't of the errour of it; and accordingly did, upon conference with the Biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> ſubmit himſelf to the determination of the Church, as appears from your own Authour, <hi>Fox vol.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 653.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="example">
                  <head>The Laſt Example.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Order of Middlebrough,</hi> which is no ways applicable to the Quakers Caſe, who have refuſed to pay Church-duties, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98333:24"/>robb'd the Royal Exchequer, which is partly ſupplied out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ths and firſt-fruits.</p>
                  <p>But why do you urge theſe Examples, or trouble his Majeſty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd the Parliament with your Plea, to be exempted from taking an Oath? becauſe (forſooth) your conſcience will not allow you to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>rear, when you actually do ſwear in as ſolemn and auguſt a form <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 'tis poſſible for the tongue of man to expreſſe, even then when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to ſay you dare not ſwear, <hi>pag.</hi> 8. <hi>God who is the ſearcher of hearts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, that it is with holy reſpect, &amp;c.</hi> juſt like that ſullen boy, whom when his mother commanded to ſay, good morrow; to his godfather, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>ſiſted in a ſilent dump, till he was ſoundly baſted, and then blub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> out this outery, <hi>I cannot ſay, good morrow, not I.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
